<!-- <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>-->
<!-- Generated by Pandoc using pretext.lua -->


<pretext>


<article>


	<p>
		2em
	</p>

	<p>
		Erich McAlister<!-- linebreak -->Department of Mathematics<!-- linebreak -->Fort Lewis College<!-- linebreak -->1000 Rim Dr.<!-- linebreak -->Durango, Co 81301<!-- linebreak -->mcalister_e@fortlewis.edu
	</p>

	<p>
		  2020 by Erich McAlister
	</p>

	<p>
		3em
	</p>

	<p>
		<image source='license.png'/><!-- linebreak -->This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. To view a copy of this license, visit<!-- linebreak -->http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/.
	</p>

	<p>
		1ex
	</p>

	<p>
		2em
	</p>

	<p>
		2em
	</p>


	<section xml:id="arithmetic-with-numbers">
		<title>Arithmetic with Numbers</title>

		<p>
			Before we begin doing algebra we will take some time to discuss the arithmetic operations that are used in algebra. These operations (addition, subtraction, multiplication, division, and exponents) are familiar to anyone taking an algebra course. However, it’s possible they were learned so long ago that a complete understanding was unnecessary at the time. In this chapter we will develop an intuitive understanding of these basic operations using practical terms and grounding metaphors as described in <q>Where Mathematics Comes Form</q> by Lakoff and Nunez. Equipped with a fluent understanding of arithmetic, algebra (which is <q>just a variety of arithmetic</q> according to Isaac Asimov) will ultimately become as intuitive and useful as arithmetic.
		</p>


		<subsection xml:id="addition-subtraction-and-multiplication">
			<title>Addition, Subtraction, and Multiplication</title>

			<p>
				Algebra is ultimately about applying some procedure, or sequence of procedures, to numbers, and asking which numbers yield some desired result. To this end, we need to conceptualize numbers more dynamically than just as a way of counting objects. In the following table we present a way to conceptualize numbers as positions on a line, and the basic operations as movements.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
<!-- div attr= xml:id="tab:a"-->
<table>
<caption>Addition, Subtraction, and Multiplication as Motions on the Line</caption>
  <tabular top="medium">
    <row bottom="medium">
      <cell left="medium">
         Positions and Sizes
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        Numbers
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
         Location on a Line
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
        <m>\longrightarrow</m>
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        Number
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
        Center of the Line
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
        <m>\longrightarrow</m>
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        <m>0</m>
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
        Position to the Right of Center
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
        <m>\longrightarrow</m>
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        Positive Number
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
        Position to the Left of Center
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
        <m>\longrightarrow</m>
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        Negative Number
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
        One Step to the Right
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
        <m>\longrightarrow</m>
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        1
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
        Given a position <m>a</m>, the position that is the same distance from the center on  the opposite side
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
        <m>\longrightarrow</m>
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        <m>-a</m>
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
        Starting from   <m>a</m>, and moving  the same distance that <m>b</m> is from the center
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
        <m>\longrightarrow</m>
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        <m>a+b</m>
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
        Starting from <m>a</m>, and moving the distance in the opposite direction that <m>b</m> is from the center
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
        <m>\longrightarrow</m>
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        <m>a-b</m>
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
        When <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are positive, the number whose size relative to <m>b</m> is the same as the size of <m>a</m> relative to <m>1</m>
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
        <m>\longrightarrow</m>
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        <m>ab</m>
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
        <m>a</m> is to the right of <m>b</m>
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
        <m>\longrightarrow</m>
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        <m>b\lt a</m>
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell left="medium">
        <m>a</m> is to the left of <m>b</m>
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
        <m>\longrightarrow</m>
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
        <m>a\lt b</m>
      </cell>
    </row>
    <row bottom="medium">
      <cell left="medium">
      </cell>
      <cell halign="center">
      </cell>
      <cell right="medium">
      </cell>
    </row>
  </tabular>
</table>


<!--</div attr= xml:id="tab:a">--><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

			<p>
				In order to understand what’s going on here, it will be useful to draw pictures. This is a picture of the real number line that you’ve probably seen before:<!-- linebreak -->
			</p>
			
<figure xml:id="fig1_1">
    <caption>The basic number line.</caption>
    <image source="images/fig1_1" width="100%"/>
</figure>


			<p>
				This picture does not show us much, so let’s show one with some generic numbers <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, where both <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are positive with <m>b&gt;a</m>.
			</p>

<figure xml:id="fig1_2">
    <caption>A number line with two  positive numbers labeled.</caption>
    	<image source="images/fig1_2" width="100%"/>
</figure>	

			<p>
				To represent <m>a+b</m> and <m>a-b</m> geometrically, we first measure out the distance <m>b</m> is to the right of zero, then move that far to the right of <m>a</m> for <m>a+b</m> and move that distance to the left of <m>a</m> for <m>a-b</m>.
			</p>

<figure xml:id="fig:addsubt1">
    <caption>Addition and subtraction of positive numbers.</caption>
    	<image source="images/addsubt1" width="100%"/>
</figure>	

			<p>
				In Figure <xref ref="fig:addsubt1" />, since <m>b&gt;a</m> we end up to the left of zero when we subtract <m>b</m> from <m>a</m>. This should make sense; if you take away more than you started out with, you end up with a deficit.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 1.1</term>.
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em>With <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> in the same positions as in Figure <xref ref="fig:addsubt1" />, draw <m>b+a</m>. What do you notice about <m>a+b</m> in relation to <m>b+a</m>?</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>Now draw <m>b-a</m>. Is the same relationship true for <m>a-b</m> and <m>b-a</m>?</em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 1.2</term>. <em>Draw a number line with numbers <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> on it, but this time make <m>a</m> positive and <m>b</m> negative. Is <m>a+b</m> to the right or left of <m>a</m>? Explain.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 1.3</term>. <em>Explain why <m>0+a = a</m> for any number <m>a</m>.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			<p>
				One of the important ideas in algebra is that of <term>inverse operations</term>. We can see this idea by looking at subtraction. Observe that if <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are numbers, then <m>a+b-b = a</m>. This may seem obvious, especially if you draw it on the number line. However, the concept is very important; <em>the inverse of adding <m>b</m> to <m>a</m> is subtracting <m>b</m>. We may say that subtracting <q>undoes</q> addition or that when you add and subtract the same quantity they <q>cancel each other</q>.</em>
			</p>

			<p>
				Multiplication of real numbers is more difficult to visualize geometrically than addition or subtraction. The fundamental idea is that of stretching, with <m>1</m> being a basic unit of measurement. Let’s start with <m>b</m> being any positive number and <m>a=1.5</m>. We see that <m>1</m> fits into <m>a</m> exactly <m>1.5</m> times. Since <m>ab</m> must have the same size relative to <m>b</m> as <m>a</m> does to <m>1</m>, <m>b</m> must fit into <m>ab</m> exactly <m>1.5</m> times. Think of this as stretching <m>b</m> by a factor of <m>a</m> when <m>a&gt;1</m>.<!-- linebreak -->
			</p>

<figure xml:id="fig:mult1">
    <caption>The same number of copies of <m>b</m> are in <m>ab</m> as copies of <m>1</m> are in <m>a</m>.</caption>
    	<image source="images/mult1" width="100%"/>
</figure>


			<p>
				If <m>a</m> is smaller than <m>1</m>, for example <m>a = 0.75</m>, then you don’t get a whole copy of <m>1</m> in <m>a</m>, you only have <m>75\%</m> of one. This means you will only get <m>75\%</m> of a copy of <m>b</m> in <m>ab</m>. In the case when <m>a&lt;1</m>, we think of <m>ab</m> as a squeeze of <m>b</m> by a factor of <m>a</m>.<!-- linebreak -->
			</p>

			<p>
				An important case happens when one of the two numbers is a whole number (an integer). If <m>n</m> is a positive integer, then <m>1</m> fits into <m>n</m> exactly <m>n</m> times. Hence, if <m>b</m> is positive, <m>b</m> will fit into <m>nb</m> exactly <m>n</m> times. Let’s view this on the number line with <m>n=5</m>:
			</p>

			<p>
				The key observation here is that when you add <m>b</m> to itself <m>n</m> times you get the same result as when you multiply <m>b</m> by <m>n</m>. In other words, <em>multiplication by a positive integer represents repeated addition. This is where the terminology <q><m>n</m> times <m>b</m></q> comes from; we’re taking <m>b</m> and adding it to itself <m>n</m> times.</em>
			</p>

			<p>
			Note that this gives us two <em> different </em> ways of thinking of multiplication; it represents repeated addition when the multiplier is positive and whole, but represents stretching or compression in other cases. We use the mental representation that makes the most sense for a given problem. This may seem confusing at first, but being aware of having several representations of mathematical objects, and knowing when you use them, is a key skill in truly understanding mathematics.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 1.4</term>. <em>Explain why <m>0a = 0</m> and <m>1a=a</m> for any number <m>a</m>.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 1.5</term>. <em>If <m>a</m> is a number between <m>3</m> and <m>4</m>, what is the possible range of values for</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>a+12</m>?</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>12a</m>?</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>12a+4</m>? Note: Only <m>a</m> is multiplied by <m>12</m>, the <m>4</m> is not multiplied by <m>12</m>.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 1.6</term>. <em>Explain why <m>ab</m> is equal to <m>ba</m> when <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are both positive integers.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			<p>
				Lastly, let’s think about multiplying negative numbers. Recall from Table <xref ref="tab:a" /> that if <m>a</m> is a number, then <m>-a</m> is the same distance from <m>0</m>, but on the other side. Multiplying negative numbers extends this idea. When <m>b</m> is any number and <m>a</m> is a negative number, then <m>ab</m> is the number with the same squeeze or stretch factor applied to <m>b</m> as if <m>a</m> were positive, but flipped to the other side of zero. For instance if <m>b</m> is positive, then <m>-0.75b</m> is the number <m>75\%</m> as far from <m>0</m> as <m>b</m>, flipped to the other side of <m>0</m> from <m>b</m>.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 1.7</term>. <em>Explain why the following statements are true using pictures and words to represent the numbers involved:</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em>A positive number times a positive number is positive.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>A positive number times a negative number is negative.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>A negative number times a negative number is positive.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>If <m>a</m> is any number, multiplying <m>a</m> by <m>-1</m> is the same as <m>-a</m>.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

		</subsection>

		<subsection xml:id="division-and-fractions">
			<title>Division and Fractions</title>


			<subsubsection xml:id="division-and-multiplication">
				<title>Division and Multiplication</title>

				<p>
					We begin with our basic intuitive metaphors for fractions:<!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
				<p>
					Fractions as Pieces of a Whole
				</p>

				<table>
					<caption></caption>
					<tabular>
					<row header="yes">
						<cell halign="left"><em>Positions and Sizes</em></cell>
						<cell halign="left"></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><em>Numbers</em></cell>
					</row>
					<row class="odd">
						<cell halign="left">Starting at <m>0</m>, the distance so that <m>b</m> steps of that size will be <m>1</m>.</cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>\longrightarrow</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>\frac{1}{b}</m></cell>
					</row>
					</tabular>
				</table>

				<p>
					Starting at <m>0</m>, the distance so that <m>b</m> steps of that size will be <m>a</m>. <m>\longrightarrow</m> <m>\frac{a}{b}</m>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

				<p>
					The metaphors of this table assume <m>b</m> is a positive integer so that we may use the idea of multiplication as repeated addition to reach a more formal understanding of division.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>Key Concept - Multiplication and Division as Inverse Operations of One Another</term>
				</p>

				<p>
					Since taking <m>b</m> steps of size <m>\frac{a}{b}</m> reaches <m>a</m>, we have the following identity: <me>b\cdot\frac{a}{b} = a.</me> When <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are not integers, we use this identity to  what <m>\frac{a}{b}</m> is: <em>For any numbers <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, <m>\frac{a}{b}</m> is the unique number such that when it is multiplied by <m>b</m> results in <m>a</m>. In other words, </em>division by <m>b</m> is the inverse operation of multiplying by <m>b</m>. Likewise, division is the inverse operation of multiplication.**
				</p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 1.8</term>. <em>Explain why <m>\dfrac{a}{a} = 1</m>.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 1.9</term>. <em>What does <m>a \cdot \dfrac{1}{b}</m> mean?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>Fundamental Fraction Properties:</term>
				</p>

				<p>
					There are four fundamental properties that we must internalize about fraction in order to do arithmetic with them:
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<m>\dfrac{a}{a} = 1</m>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>\dfrac{a}{1} = a</m>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>x\cdot\dfrac{a}{b} = \dfrac{xa}{b}</m>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>\dfrac{xa}{xb} = \dfrac{a}{b}</m>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p>

				<p>
					(From http://gdaymath.com/lessons/fractions/2-5-the-key-fraction-property/)
				</p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 1.10</term>.
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em>What do you get when you multiply <m>\dfrac{b}{a}</m> by <m>\dfrac{a}{b}</m>?</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>What do you get when you multiply <m>\dfrac{1}{\left(\frac ab \right)}</m> by <m>\frac{a}{b}</m>?</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Explain why <m>\dfrac{1}{\left(\frac{a}{b}\right)} = \dfrac{b}{a}</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 1.11</term>. <em>(Multiplying Fractions) Explain why <m>\dfrac{a}{b}\cdot\dfrac{c}{d} = \dfrac{ac}{bd}</m> using the fundamental fraction properties.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					We can also use the stretch/squeeze metaphor of multiplication to give a geometric interpretation of <m>\frac{a}{b}</m> when <m>b</m> is not an integer. To do this, let’s let <m>r = \frac{a}{b}</m>, and assume <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are still positive (since negatives just reflect to the other side of zero). Our goal is to figure out where <m>r</m> is on the number line. To do this, we first do a manipulation: <me>\frac{a}{b} = r \Longleftrightarrow a = rb.</me> This manipulation used the fact that multiplication by <m>b</m> undoes division by <m>b</m>. From this manipulated equation we see that <m>r = \frac{a}{b}</m> is the number that when stretched (if <m>b&gt;1</m>) or squeezed (if <m>0&lt;b&lt;1</m>) by <m>b</m> gives you <m>a</m>.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 1.12</term>. <em>Explain the following two statements:</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em>If <m>b</m> is very large, then <m>\frac{1}{b}</m> is very small.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>If <m>b</m> is very close to zero, but still positive, then <m>\frac{1}{b}</m> is very large.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					Now let’s consider why we must say <m>\frac{a}{0}</m> is undefined no matter what <m>a</m> is.
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					<term>Reason 1:</term> Consider the fraction <m>\frac{1}{b}</m> where <m>b</m> is positive. We know that if <m>b</m> is very close to zero, then <m>\frac{1}{b}</m> will be very large. For example, <m>\frac{1}{0.0001} = 10000</m> because if you squeeze <m>10000</m> by a factor of <m>0.0001</m> you get <m>1</m>. However, you can always make the <m>b</m> smaller and get a bigger number. This means that <m>\frac{1}{0}</m> would need to be larger than every positive number. But no such number exists, so <m>\frac{1}{0}</m> must be undefined.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<term>Reason 2:</term> The expression <m>\frac{a}{0}</m> should represent the number that when multiplied by <m>0</m> results in <m>a</m>. However, any number multiplied by zero must be zero. For this reason, if <m>a</m> is not zero, then <m>\frac{a}{0}\cdot 0</m> cannot equal <m>a</m>. Thus we say that <m>\frac{a}{0}</m> cannot represent a number if <m>a\neq 0</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					To really see why the expression <m>\frac{0}{0}</m> is undefined, you need an idea from Calculus, but you can get a feel for why it must be undefined in the next question.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 1.13</term>. <em>Give a short reason why the expression <m>\frac{0}{0}</m> could represent either <m>0</m> or <m>1</m>.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="apples-and-oranges-units-and-dimensional-analysis">
				<title>Apples and Oranges: Units and Dimensional Analysis</title>

				<p>
					So far we have only talked about multiplying and dividing fractions. These operations with fractions are fundamentally easier then addition and subtraction. In order to build a useful metaphor of how to add and subtract fractions, it will be useful to talk about units of measurement. Not only will understanding units and unit conversion be useful for understanding fractions, but it is extremely useful in the sciences.
				</p>


				<paragraphs xml:id="dimensional-analysis-and-the-factor-label-method-of-unit-conversion">
					<title>Dimensional Analysis and the Factor-Label Method of Unit Conversion</title>

					<p>
						A very common task in physics or chemistry classes involves converting between units of measurement of quantities of the same dimension. The simplest way to do this is to treat the units of measurement as numbers multiplied by the numerical quantity in those units. So if we say a rod is two meters long, we would write the mathematical expression <me>\mbox{length} = 2 \mbox{m},</me> where <m>\mbox{m}</m> is the abbreviation for meters multiplied by the number <m>2</m>. Since the unit name (the label) is multiplied by a number it is a factor in that expression. This is why we call this treatment of unit names as numbers the <em>factor-label method. By treating the units as number, we can use our prior knowledge of arithmetic operations to make conversions.</em>
					</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
					<p>
						<term>Example 1.14</term>. Suppose we need to convert <m>12</m> ounces into milliliters. This is a legal conversion because both ounces and milliliters have the same dimension; both units describe volume. In order to make the conversion, we write down an equation with the number of one of the units in another: <me>1 \mbox{oz} = 29.5735 \mbox{mL}.</me> Form this equation, we can divide to obtain <m>1</m> without units in two different ways: <me>1=\frac{1 \mbox{oz}}{29.5735\mbox{mL}}\ \ \mbox{and} \ \ 1=\frac{29.5735 \mbox{mL}}{1 \mbox{oz}}.</me> Multiplying the quantity <m>12 \mbox{oz}</m> by either of these expressions for <m>1</m> must leave it unchanged. In order to obtain final units of <m>\mbox{mL}</m>, we will multiply by the second because <m>\frac{\mbox{oz}}{\mbox{oz}} = 1</m> (we say the units of ounces cancel). <me>12\mbox{oz} = 12\mbox{oz}\cdot\frac{29.5735\mbox{mL}}{1\mbox{oz}} = 12\cdot 29.5735 \mbox{mL} = 354.882 \mbox{mL}.</me>
					</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
					<p>
						<term>Example 1.15</term>. A <m>rope</m> is a unit of length equal to 20ft (it isn’t used much anymore). Suppose an old city plan shows that the street is <m>2\ \mbox{rope}</m> wide with a sidewalk that is <m>2</m>yd on each side. What is the total width of the street plus both sidewalks? You may be able to see quickly that the answer is 52ft, but let’s do all the conversions carefully.
					</p>

					<p>
						First, note that we will need to add the width of both sidewalks to the width of the street. It isn’t convenient to convert ropes to yards or yards to ropes; it makes the most sense to convert everything to feet. Let’s write all our conversion equations: <me>1 \mbox{street} = 2 \mbox{rope}\ ,\ 1\mbox{rope} = 20\mbox{ft}\ ,\ 1\mbox{sidewalk} = 2\mbox{yd}\ ,\ 1\mbox{yd} = 3\mbox{ft}.</me> So we get the following: <me>\begin{aligned}
1\mbox{street} + 2\mbox{sidewalk} &amp; = &amp; 1\mbox{street}\cdot\frac{2\mbox{rope}}{\mbox{street}}\cdot\frac{20\mbox{ft}}{\mbox{rope}} + 2\mbox{sidewalk}\cdot\frac{2\mbox{yd}}{\mbox{sidewalk}}\cdot\frac{3\mbox{ft}}{\mbox{yd}}\\\\
\ &amp; = &amp; 40\mbox{ft}+12\mbox{ft}= 52\mbox{ft}\end{aligned}</me>
					</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
					<p>
						<term>Question 1.16</term>. <em>Suppose a person is on a train that is moving <m>100</m> km/hr and they run from the rear of the train to the front at a rate of <m>8</m> m/s. How fast is this person moving relative to the ground in m/s? Note that <m>1</m> km = <m>1000</m> m and <m>1</m> hr = <m>3600</m> s.</em>
					</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
					<p>
						<term>Example 1.17</term>. The factor-label method of dimensional analysis can also be used to change the way we look at a changing quantity through multiplication and division. For instance, suppose a tank contains a salt water solution with a concentration of <m>2</m> grams of salt per liter. If the tank is drained at a rate of <m>10</m> mL/s, at what rate is salt leaving the tank in g/s?
					</p>

					<p>
						 To solve this problem, let’s first convert the draining rate into L/s: <me>10 \frac{\mbox{mL}}{\mbox{s}} = 10 \frac{\mbox{mL}}{\mbox{s}}\cdot \frac{1}{1000}\frac{\mbox{L}}{\mbox{mL}} = \frac{1}{100} \frac{\mbox{L}}{\mbox{s}}.</me> Now we just need to multiply quantities to arrive at the correct units for the rate of salt leaving the tank: <me>2\frac{\mbox{g}}{\mbox{L}}\cdot\frac{1}{100}\frac{\mbox{L}}{\mbox{s}} = \frac{2}{100}\frac{\mbox{g}}{\mbox{s}} = 0.02\frac{\mbox{g}}{\mbox{s}}</me>
					</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

					<p>
						The cost of fuel for a riverboat is <m>\$100</m> per hour when moving <m>10</m> miles per hour. In addition to fuel costs, the operating cost (paying the crew etc.) is <m>\$625</m> per hour. What is the total cost in <m>\$</m>/mi when the boat is moving <m>10</m> miles per hour?
					</p>

				</paragraphs>
			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="adding-and-subtracting-fractions">
				<title>Adding and Subtracting Fractions</title>

				<p>
					Now that we have thought about real world units of measurement, and we can convert units that measure the same dimensional quantity, we can introduce a useful metaphor for adding, subtracting, and comparing fractions:
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
				<p>
					Fractions as Units
				</p>

				<table>
					<caption></caption>
					<tabular>
					<row header="yes">
						<cell halign="left"><em>Units of Measurement</em></cell>
						<cell halign="left"></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><em>Numbers</em></cell>
					</row>
					<row class="odd">
						<cell halign="left"> </cell>
						<cell halign="left"> </cell>
						<cell halign="left"></cell>
					</row>
					<row class="even">
						<cell halign="left">Dimensional Unit of <q><m>b</m>-ths</q></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>\rightarrow</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>\frac{1}{b}</m></cell>
					</row>
					</tabular>
				</table><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

				<p>
					Often it will be best to think of fractions as units of length (like when we think of numbers as positions on a line), but they could be areas, volumes, etc. Here we will think of the number <m>1</m> as the basic unit of measurement. Then a <m>b</m>-th is the unit that goes into the basic unit <m>b</m> times. For instance, if we are thinking of <m>1</m> as <m>1</m> foot, then <m>\frac{1}{12}</m> is one inch because there are 12 inches in one foot.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 1.18</term>. <em>For each of the following basic units, what fraction does the given quantity represent? For instance, if the basic unit is one yard, then <m>1</m> foot is <m>\frac{1}{3}</m> because there are three feet in a yard.</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Basic Unit: 1 kilometer. <m>100</m> meters <m>=</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Basic Unit: 1 cup. <m>1</m> ounce <m>=</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Basic Unit: 1 meter. <m>10</m> centimeters <m>=</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Basic Unit: 1 gallon. <m>3</m> quarts <m>=</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Basic Unit: 1 football field. <m>40</m> yards <m>=</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Basic Unit: 1 tablespoon. <m>8</m> teaspoons <m>=</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					Now let’s revisit the example of ropes and yards from the last section. In order to add two ropes to four yards, it was necessary to convert both ropes and yards into a smaller unit that went into both ropes and yards evenly. Specifically, both were converted to feet to get a total of 52 feet. When we are just working with numbers we do something very similar; we find a common denominator.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 1.19</term>. Let’s add <m>\frac{3}{5}</m> to <m>\frac{1}{2}</m>. To get started we can look at it pictorially with <m>\frac{1}{3}</m> and <m>\frac{1}{7}</m> on number lines:
				</p>

				<p>
					[fig:addfracs1]
				</p>

				<p>
					If we divide <m>\frac{1}{5}</m> in half and <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> into five pieces, we find that <m>\frac{1}{10}</m> goes into both <m>\frac{1}{5}</m> and <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> evenly.
				</p>

				<p>
					[fig:addfracs2]
				</p>

				<p>
					Now we see the addition: <me>\frac{3}{5} + \frac{1}{2} = \frac{6}{10}+\frac{5}{10} = \frac{11}{10}.</me> This is the geometric way of visualizing the process known as known as <q>cross multiplying</q>. That is when you multiply each part of a fraction with a fraction equal to one in order to have a common denominator: <me>\frac{3}{5}+\frac{1}{2} = \frac{2}{2}\cdot\frac{3}{5} + \frac{5}{5}\cdot\frac{1}{2} = \frac{11}{10}.</me>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

				<p>
					One thing we usually try to find is the  common denominator between two fractions. Thinking in terms of units, this is like finding the largest possible unit that goes into both quantities evenly. In the example given above we could have used <m>\frac{1}{20}</m> to go into <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> and <m>\frac{3}{5}</m> evenly and obtained <me>\frac{3}{5}+\frac{1}{2} = \frac{22}{20}.</me> However, that makes the numbers we are dealing with larger for no reason. This would be like converting both ropes and yards into inches; it’s possible, but unnecessary.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 1.20</term>. <em>Draw a picture to carefully perform the following:</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>\frac12 + \frac13</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>\frac12+\frac14</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>\frac13+\frac14</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 1.21</term>. <em>Perform the indicated additions and subtractions:</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>\frac{3}{7}+\frac{9}{8}</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>\frac{7}{3}+\frac{8}{9}</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>\frac{1}{2} + \frac{1}{3} - \frac{1}{4}</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>\frac{15}{3} + \frac{14}{7}</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>
		</subsection>

		<subsection xml:id="exponents">
			<title>Exponents</title>

			<p>
				Most fundamentally, exponents represent repeated multiplication in the way that multiplication represents repeated addition.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
			<p>
				Multiplication is to Addition as Exponents are to Multiplication
			</p>

			<table>
				<caption></caption>
				<tabular>
				<row header="yes">
					<cell halign="left"><em>Multiplication as Repeated Addition</em></cell>
					<cell halign="left"></cell>
					<cell halign="left"><em>Exponents as Repeated Multiplication</em></cell>
				</row>
				<row class="odd">
					<cell halign="left"><m>na = \underbrace{a+ a +\cdots + a}_\text{$n$ times}</m></cell>
					<cell halign="left"><m>\longrightarrow</m></cell>
					<cell halign="left"><m>a^n = \underbrace{a\cdot a \cdot\cdots \cdot a}_\text{$n$ times}</m></cell>
				</row>
				</tabular>
			</table><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

			<p>
				Based on this idea, we can see the following properties of exponents:
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
			<p>
				<term>Properties of Exponents</term>
			</p>

			<p><ul>
				<li>
							<p>
				<m>a^na^m = a^{n+m}</m>. Eg <m>2^{3}\cdot 2^4 = 2\cdot 2\cdot 2\cdot 2\cdot 2\cdot 2\cdot 2 = 2^7 = 128</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				If <m>a\neq 0</m>, <m>\frac{a^n}{a^m} = a^{n-m}</m>. Eg <m>\frac{3^{5}}{3^2} = \frac{3\cdot 3\cdot 3\cdot 3\cdot 3}{3\cdot 3} = 3^3 = 27</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<m>(a^n)^m = a^{nm}</m>. Eg <m>(2^{3})^2 = (2\cdot 2\cdot 2)\cdot(2\cdot 2\cdot 2) = 2^6 = 64</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<m>(ab)^n = a^nb^n</m>. Eg <m>(2\cdot 3)^2 = (2\cdot 3)\cdot (2\cdot 3) = 2\cdot 2\cdot 3\cdot 3</m> <m>= 2^2\cdot3^2 = 36</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<m>\left(\frac{a}{b}\right)^{n} = \frac{a^n}{b^n}</m>. Eg <m>\left(\frac{2}{3}\right)^2 = \frac{2}{3}\cdot\frac{2}{3} = \frac{4}{9}</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ul></p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

			<p>
				More subtlety arises when making sense out of zero, negative, and fractional exponents. The problem is that we don’t know what it means to multiply a number by itself zero times, a negative number of times, or a fractional number of times. Because of this, we use the properties listed above to define zero, negative, and fractional exponents.
			</p>

			<p>
				First, let’s consider what <m>a^0</m> should equal, where <m>a</m> is a nonzero number. We know that if <m>n</m> is any number that <m>0 = n-n</m>. Using the second exponent property given above, we have <me>a^0 = a^{n-n} = \frac{a^n}{a^n}.</me> Since <m>\frac{a^n}{a^n} = 1</m>, we define <m>a^0 = 1</m> whenever <m>a</m> is not zero (<m>0^0</m> is undefined).
			</p>

			<p>
				Now consider a negative exponent, <m>a^{-n}</m>. Here we use the first two exponent properties to arrive at what <m>a^{-n}</m> must be. We have <me>a^{n}a^{-n} = a^{n+(-n)} = a^{n-n} = a^{0} = 1.</me> Shortening this string of equalities, we have <m>a^{n}a^{-n} = 1</m>. Now we divide both sides by <m>a^{n}</m> to get <m>a^{-n} = \frac{1}{a^{n}}</m>. In words, a negative exponent denotes division by the same number with a positive exponent.
			</p>

			<p>
				Finally, let’s consider what <m>a^{\frac{1}{n}}</m> should be. This time we’ll use the third exponent property that a power raised to a power reults in the exponents being multiplied. Thus we have, <me>(a^{\frac{1}{n}})^n  = a^{\frac{n}{n}} = a^{1} = a.</me> So <m>a^{\frac{1}{n}}</m> is the number that when raised to the <m>n</m>-th power results in <m>a</m>. This is exactly a description of the <m>n</m>-th root, <m>\sqrt[n]{a}</m>. Going slightly further with the third exponent property, we have <m>a^\frac{m}{n} = \sqrt[n]{a^m} = (\sqrt[n]{a})^m</m>.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 1.22</term>. <em>Justify the last sentence of the last paragraph.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			<p>
				So in summary we have:
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
			<p>
				<term>Zero, Negative, and Fractional Exponents</term>
			</p>

			<p><ul>
				<li>
							<p>
				<m>a^0 = 1</m> when <m>a\neq 0</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<m>a^{-n} = \frac{1}{a^n}</m>: negative exponents denote division.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<m>a^{\frac{m}{n}} = \sqrt[n]{a^m} = (\sqrt[n]{a})^m</m>: denominators in fractional exponents denote roots.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ul></p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 1.23</term>. <em>Evaluate the following without a calculator. Make sure you do it as efficiently as possible using properties of exponents.</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>4^{\frac{3}{2}}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>9^{-\frac{1}{2}}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>(\frac{1}{27})^{-\frac{2}{3}}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\frac{1}{7^{-2}}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\frac{10^9}{10^7}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>16^{\frac{5}{4}}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 1.24</term>. <em>Use properties of exponents to write the following in a simpler way using only positive exponents.</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>-4^0</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>z^{-3} \cdot z^3</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>w^{-4} \cdot(4x)^0 \cdot x^6</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\dfrac{5t^3}{t^{-6}}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\left(\dfrac{a^2}{b^3} \right)^{-1}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\left(\dfrac{x}{3} \right)^{-2}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

		</subsection>

		<subsection xml:id="parentheses-and-order-of-operations">
			<title>Parentheses and Order of Operations</title>

			<p>
				Each of the previous sections in this chapter have focused mostly on one mathematical operation at a time. However, it is often the case that more than one operation is performed. Difficulty arises because the order in which operations occur matters; different orders yield different results. For example, let’s consider the two mathematical processes described below:
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				Take the number two, add three to it, then multiply the result by four.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				Take the number two, multiply it by four, then add three to the result.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p>

			<p>
				The two operations are adding three and multiplying by four, but performed in different orders. In the first order, two gets shifted up to five, then stretched out by a factor of four, yielding an end result of 20. In the second, two gets stretched out to eight, then that is shifted up by three, yielding an end result of 11. In order to distinguish these two orders using mathematical notation, we use parentheses to enclose those procedures that are to be performed first. Specifically, we have the following symbolic representations corresponding to the verbal descriptions given above:
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<m>4(2+3) = 20</m>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<m>(4\cdot 2)+3 = 11</m>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p>

			<p>
				In a mathematical expression, any procedures that are enclosed in parentheses are meant to be performed before those procedures outside that set of parentheses. One way to think of parentheses is that whatever is inside them must be combined/simplified to a single quantity before proceeding.
			</p>

			<p>
				What about the other operations? You probably have learned the answer earlier in your mathematical lives. Indeed, in the last section we used parentheses in expressions with exponents without really explaining their use. You may have even encountered some mnemonic device for remembering order of operations. Because being able to execute the operations is more important than just remembering, we will catalog the order of operations rules here, then use them in some problems.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
			<p>
				<term>Order of Operations</term>
			</p>

			<p><ul>
				<li>
							<p>
				Procedures enclosed in parentheses should be performed before any operations outside those parentheses.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				Exponents should be applied second, but only to the object that the exponent is directly above and to the right of.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				Multiplication and/or division should be performed before addition and/or subtraction unless otherwise indicated by parentheses. In other words, in an expression only involving addition and multiplication, those individual multiplications are in parentheses.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				Division is just multiplication by the reciprocal, so division and multiplication can be performed in either order.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				Subtraction is just addition of a negative, so subtraction and addition can be performed in either order.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ul></p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

			<p>
				These aren’t actually too hard to keep track of, just as long as you remember that their purpose is to remove ambiguity from mathematical notation. For instance, without these rules <m>4\cdot 2 +3</m> could be interpreted either as <m>11</m> or <m>20</m>. These rules make sure that we all agree that it is <m>11</m>.
			</p>

			<p>
				In addition to multiplications having understood (but not written down) parentheses around them, there are often understood parentheses in fractions. For instance, if we write <me>\frac{1}{3+7},</me> we will understand that <m>3+7</m> is to be performed first. Usually this isn’t an issue when fractions are written with horizontal lines, but we would have to use parentheses to write it on a single line as <m>1/(3+7)</m>.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 1.25</term>. <em>Evaluate each of the following quantities without a calculator. If your answer is a fraction, give it in reduced form.</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>3\cdot 3^{-2}\cdot(-1)^2</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>-3^2+\frac{64}{2^3}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>(-5+2)^3+12</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\frac{(3+2)^2}{4} - \left(\frac{2-7}{2}\right)^2</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>4+5/7</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>(4+5)/7</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 1.26</term>. <em>Verbally describe the sequence of operations performed on the number <m>a</m> in the correct order.</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>2(a+1)</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>2a+1</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>1-3\left(\frac{a}{2}+4\right)</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>3-2(a+5)</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			<p>
				Now we come to the end of our chapter on arithmetic with numbers. Those of you with some exposure to algebra may now say, <q>This is easy, but algebra is very different and difficult.</q> The truth is that is we keep the representations of arithmetic operations from this chapter in mind, algebra will not be that difficult.
			</p>

		</subsection>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="algebraic-expressions">
		<title>Algebraic Expressions</title>

		<p>
			The basic object in the study of algebra is what is known as an <em>algebraic expression. These are just mathematical expressions that contain variables. Think of a variable as a generic number (as one goes further in mathematics one deals with variables that are no longer just numbers). In the last chapter we used variables to describe general arithmetic operations. Variables and algebraic expressions are essential to applying mathematics in science and engineering. In these fields, one needs to know how one numerical quantity will affect another. These relationships between two quantities are known as functions, which are often written using an algebraic expression.</em>
		</p>


		<subsection xml:id="examples-of-algebraic-expressions">
			<title>Examples of Algebraic Expressions</title>

			<p>
				Let’s look at some basic algebraic expressions, describe them verbally, and evaluate them for some values of the variables.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
			<p>
				<term>Example 2.1</term>. Consider the algebraic expression <me>(3x+1)^2-2.</me> This expression only contains one variable, <m>x</m>. We can substitute values for <m>x</m> and get values of the algebraic expression. For instance, if we evaluate it at <m>x=2</m> we get <me>(3\cdot 2+1)^2 -2 = 7^2-2 = 47.</me> If we evaluate this expression at <m>x=-2</m> we have <me>(3\cdot(-2) +1)^2 -2 = (-5)^2 -2 = 23,</me> Evaluating algebraic expressions isn’t that hard provided you keep track of your order of operations. A more difficult, but very much related skill is to read an algebraic expression and verbally express what is being done to the variable(s) in the correct order. In this expression we start with the value of <m>x</m> and
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				multiply <m>x</m> by three,
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				add one to the result of <term>S1</term>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				square the result of <term>S2</term>, and finally
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				subtract two from the result of <term>S3</term>.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p>

			<p>
				
			</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

			<p>
				This idea of verbally describing algebraic expressions and understanding the steps that they represent is important for seeing algebraic expressions as something other than just a bunch of random symbols on a page.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
			<p>
				Algebraic Expressions Describe Processes Performed on Variables
			</p>

			<p>
				<em>Algebraic Expression</em> <m>\longrightarrow</m> <em>A symbolic representation of a sequence of arithmetic operations performed in a specific order on general numbers (variables).</em> ———————— ——————- ———————————————————————————————————————————-
			</p><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 2.2</term>. <em>Write an algebraic expression that represents the following process applied to <m>x</m>:</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em>Add one to <m>x</m>,</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>square the result of <term>S1</term></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>subtract two from the result of <term>S2</term>, and finally</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>multiply the result of <term>S3</term> by <m>5</m>.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p>

			<p>
				<em>Evaluate the expression you get at <m>x=2</m>, <m>x=-2</m>, and <m>x=0</m>.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			<p>
				We will often abbreviate the result of a step <term>Sn</term> by just writing <term>Sn</term>. For example, we could just write "multiply <term>S3</term> by <m>5</m>" for the last step above.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg" xml:id="E:recip"-->
			<p>
				<term>Example 2.3</term>. Suppose we want to understand the expression <m>\frac{2}{x+1}</m>. One way to describe this process is
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				Add <m>1</m> to <m>x</m>,
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				divide <m>2</m> by <term>S1</term>.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p>

			<p>
				Note that we need to be careful in describing <term>S2</term>: we need to specify which quantity is divided by which here. We may want to think of this as a process which is being done primarily to <m>x</m>, and break it down as <m>2 \cdot \frac{1}{x+1}</m>. Then we could describe the expression by the following:
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				Add <m>1</m> to <m>x</m>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				Take the reciprocal of <term>S1</term>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				multiply the result of <term>S2</term> by <m>2</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="eg" xml:id="E:recip">-->

			<p>
				Sometimes a variable can appear more than once in an expression, which may make describing it as a single procedure more difficult. This difficulty is dealt with by thinking of a combination of procedures using order of operations.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
			<p>
				<term>Example 2.4</term>. Verbally describe the expression <me>4s^2 + 2\sqrt{s+1}.</me> If we were evaluating this at a specific value of <m>s</m>, we would perform the addition last. For this reason, we take each part that will be added together and describe them separately first. For the first term (a <em>term is a part of an algebraic expression being added to other parts):</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				Square <m>s</m>, then
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				multiply <term>S1</term> by four.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p>

			<p>
				Then we pick up with the second term:
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				Add one to <m>s</m>,
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				take the square root of <term>S3</term>, and
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				multiply <term>S4</term> by two.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p>

			<p>
				The last step is the last thing according to our order of operations:
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
				Add the result of <term>S2</term> to the result of steps <term>S5</term>. 
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 2.5</term>. <em>List the steps being performed on <m>x</m>, in order, for each of the following algebraic expressions:</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\frac{6}{2+x}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>2(x+1)^2 -5</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>3(x+2)-5(x-7)</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\frac{3}{x} - 4x^2 -1</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\frac{1}{x-a}+\frac{3}{\sqrt{x+b}}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			<p>
				Let’s finish this section with examples of algebraic expressions that you might come across in another class or the real world.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
			<p>
				<term>Example 2.6</term>. An algebraic expression commonly encountered in a first year physics course gives the height <m>h</m> of a projectile, in meters, above the ground <m>t</m> seconds after it has been launched. This expression has parameters for initial height and initial upward velocity. The expression is <me>h = -4.9t^2+v_0 t + h_0,</me> where <m>v_0</m> is the initial upward velocity in m/s and <m>h_0</m> is the initial height in meters. For instance, if we knew the initial height was <m>40</m> meters and the initial velocity was <m>0</m> m/s (if the object was dropped, not thrown), then we would have <me>h = -4.9t^2 + 40.</me> 
			</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 2.7</term>. <em>Using the expression above, with <m>h_0 = 40</m> and <m>v_0 = 0</m>, for the height, answer the following questions to the best of your ability (you may need a calculator).</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em>How high is the object after <m>2</m> seconds? <m>3</m> seconds?</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>When does the object hit the ground?</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>Is the object ever <m>50</m> meters above the ground? Justify your answer in practical terms and algebraically, if possible.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
			<p>
				<term>Example 2.8</term>. The following table gives the men’s world record times for running events as of Summer 2017, as well as the average speeds in m/s.<!-- linebreak -->
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
			<table>
				<caption></caption>
				<tabular>
				<row header="yes">
					<cell halign="center"><m>d=</m> Distance (m)</cell>
					<cell halign="center"><m>T=</m> time (s)</cell>
					<cell halign="center"><m>S=</m> speed (m/s)</cell>
				</row>
				<row class="odd">
					<cell halign="center">100</cell>
					<cell halign="center">9.58</cell>
					<cell halign="center">10.44</cell>
				</row>
				<row class="even">
					<cell halign="center">200</cell>
					<cell halign="center">19.19</cell>
					<cell halign="center">10.42</cell>
				</row>
				<row class="odd">
					<cell halign="center">400</cell>
					<cell halign="center">43.03</cell>
					<cell halign="center">9.3</cell>
				</row>
				<row class="even">
					<cell halign="center">800</cell>
					<cell halign="center">100.91</cell>
					<cell halign="center">7.93</cell>
				</row>
				<row class="odd">
					<cell halign="center">1500</cell>
					<cell halign="center">206</cell>
					<cell halign="center">7.28</cell>
				</row>
				<row class="even">
					<cell halign="center">5000</cell>
					<cell halign="center">757.35</cell>
					<cell halign="center">6.6</cell>
				</row>
				</tabular>
			</table><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

			<p>
				Using techniques from statistics or linear algebra (data fitting), it is possible to give an algebraic expression involving the distance <m>d</m> that approximately tells you the record time <m>T</m>. The expression one finds this way is <me>T = .06640993d^{1.09689}.</me> Since speed is distance divided by time, we can then formulate an expression for the speed <m>S</m> in terms of the distance <m>d</m>: <me>S = \frac{d}{T}  = \frac{d}{.06640993 d^{1.09689}} = \frac{15.05798907}{d^{.09689}}.</me> 
			</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 2.9</term>. <em>Use the expressions in the last example to answer the following questions.</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em>The expressions given above only give approximations. After all, if we could find record times with a formula we wouldn’t need to have races. Use a calculator to evaluate the expression given for <m>T</m>, for each distance, and see how well it matches the data.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>What does the expression for <m>T</m> say the record time for <m>10000</m> meters should be? Is it accurate? (Use the internet to check.)</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>Two versions of the expression for <m>S</m> are shown. Use the rules for fractions and exponents from Chapter 1 to explain why these two versions are really the same.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>In the expression for <m>S</m>, what happens to <m>S</m> as <m>d</m> gets very large (see Question 1.5a in Chapter 1)? Does this make practical sense?</em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

		</subsection>

		<subsection xml:id="equivalent-algebraic-expressions">
			<title>Equivalent Algebraic Expressions</title>

			<p>
				Two algebraic expressions are called <em>equivalent if they yield the same output no matter what is substituted into them. Thinking of algebraic expressions procedurally, we have the following characterization of equivalent algebraic expressions:</em>
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
			<p>
				Equivalent Expressions as Different Processes with the Same Result
			</p>

			<p>
				<em>Equivalent Algebraic Expressions</em> <m>\rightarrow</m> <em>Equivalent algebraic expressions are symbolic representations of different processes performed on the variables that always give the same end result.</em> ———————————— ————— ———————————————————————————————————————————————————
			</p><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

			<p>
				People who are good at algebra often speak of manipulating/simplifying algebraic expressions and putting expressions into different forms. What they are talking about is replacing an expression with an equivalent expression. The reason for manipulating expressions is that sometimes one version of an expression makes it easier to see a solution to a problem. For instance, the expression used to find the temperature in <m>^{\circ}</m>C given the temperature in <m>^{\circ}</m>F is <me>C = \frac{5}{9}F - \frac{160}{9},</me> where <m>F</m> is the temperature in <m>^{\circ}</m>F and <m>C</m> is the temperature in <m>^{\circ}</m>C. Suppose we want to know what temperature in <m>^{\circ}</m>F corresponds to <m>O^{\circ}</m>C. Even if you already know the answer is <m>32^{\circ}</m>F, the given expression does not make it obvious. However, the given expression is equivalent to the following: <me>C = \frac{5}{9}(F - 32).</me> Now the solution is more clear; if we substitute <m>F=32</m> into the expression for <m>C</m> in terms of <m>F</m>, we get <m>\frac{5}{9}(32-32) = 0</m>.
			</p>

			<p>
				Why are these two expressions equivalent? The answer here comes from the arithmetic rule known as the distributive law (to be discussed more later). We can take the second expression and distribute the <m>\frac{5}{9}</m> as follows: <me>\frac{5}{9}(F-32)  = \frac{5}{9}F - \frac{5}{9}\cdot 32 = \frac{5}{9}F-\frac{160}{9}.</me>
			</p>

			<p>
				Another example of equivalent expressions is give by Example <xref ref="E:recip" />. In this case, we used the fact that the expression <m>\frac{2}{x+1}</m> is equivalent to <m>2 \cdot \frac{1}{x+1}</m>.
			</p>

			<p>
				Fundamentally, since algebraic expressions are built using the operations of arithmetic, equivalence of algebraic expressions is determined by using rules of arithmetic. We will discuss the most commonly used ways of manipulating expressions into equivalent ones in the remainder of this section. However, we will first discuss how to tell if two expressions are inequivalent.
			</p>


			<subsubsection xml:id="inequivalent-expressions">
				<title>Inequivalent Expressions</title>

				<p>
					Two expressions are not equivalent if there are some values of the variables in the expression that yield different numbers when you substitute. So, if you plug the same number into two expressions and get different results, then the two expressions are inequivalent (assuming you did the arithmetic correctly). With practice, you’ll get good at being able to detect inequivalent expressions without even needing to substitute anything. For now, we’ll look at some important examples that sometimes trip people up.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 2.10</term>. The two expressions <m>(x+y)^2</m> and <m>x^2 + y^2</m> are  equivalent. One may detect this by noting the order in which operations are performed on <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>. In one expression you add the two variables, then square. In the other, you square each variable, then add. Based one our experience with order of operations (order matters), we think these may not be equivalent. It turns out that if you pick any two numbers for <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>, as long as neither is zero, these two expressions will evaluate to different numbers. For instance, if we substitute <m>x=1</m> and <m>y=2</m>, then the first expression gives <me>(1+2)^2 = 3^2 =9,</me> whereas the second expression gives <me>1^2+2^2 = 1+4 = 5.</me> It is also possible to see that these two expressions are inequivalent by giving the geometric representations. We begin by thinking of <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> as lengths. Then <m>(x+y)^2</m> is the area of a square whose side length is <m>x+y</m>, while <m>x^2+y^2</m> is the sum of areas of squares that fit inside the square of side length <m>x+y</m> as in the following diagram:
				</p>

				<p>
					In this figure we see that the total shaded area is <m>x^2+y^2</m> while the area of the entire square is <m>(x+y)^2</m>. If you note that the unshaded portions of the square each have area <m>xy</m>, we can see that <m>(x+y)^2</m>  equivalent to <m>x^2+2xy+y^2</m>. We will see this more symbolically in the section on distributing, expanding, and factoring. 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 2.11</term>. <em>Explain why <m>\sqrt{a^2 + b^2}</m> is not equivalent to <m>a+b</m>. Do this both by plugging in numbers and by either referring to the last example, or using the Pythagorean Theorem to explain the inequivalence geometrically.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 2.12</term>. <em>Use volumes to give a geometric explanation of why <m>(x+y)^3</m> is equivalent to <m>x^3+3x^2y+3xy^2+y^3</m>, but is not equivalent to <m>x^3+y^3</m>.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 2.13</term>. <m>\frac{1}{x}+\frac{1}{3}</m> is  equivalent to <m>\frac{2}{x+3}</m>. A simple, but perhaps not helpful, reason is because that’s not how you add fractions. Let’s make sure we really see that this is not how you add fractions. First substitute <m>x=1</m>. Then the first expression evaluates to <me>\frac{1}{1} + \frac{1}{3}=1+\frac{1}{3},</me> while the second evaluates to <me>\frac{2}{4} = \frac{1}{2}.</me> Even if you forget how to add fractions you can tell these are not equal. The first one is larger than one and the second is smaller than one. 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

				<p>
					<term>Remark:</term> It is important to note that for two expressions to be equivalent, they must evaluate to the same number for  values of the variables, not just some. For instance, in the example with squares, if <m>x=0</m> the two expressions do evaluate to the same thing. However, this does not make the expressions equivalent.
				</p>

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="reordering-and-regrouping">
				<title>Reordering and Regrouping</title>

				<p>
					Sometimes the order in which operations are performed in an algebraic expression doesn’t affect the result. Specifically, if the expression only involves addition, order of operations doesn’t tell you which one to do first because it doesn’t matter. Likewise for multiplication. Specifically, we have the following rules for addition and multiplication:
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>Commutative and Associative Laws for Addition and Multiplication</term>
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					<m>a+b = b+a</m> (addition is commutative)
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>ab=ba</m> (multiplication is commutative)
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>a+(b+c) = (a+b)+c</m> (addition is associative)
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>a(bc)=(ab)c</m> (multiplication is associative)
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

				<p>
					In Chapter 1 you were asked to explain the commutativity of addition geometrically using lengths on the number line (Question 1). To explain the commutativity of multiplication, we think of <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> as lengths of the sides of a rectangle. Using the fact that the area of a rectangle is given by <me>\mbox{Area} = \mbox{base}\times\mbox{height},</me> we can arrange our rectangle with <m>a</m> on the bottom and <m>b</m> on the side to get the area to be <m>ab</m>. If we simply rotate the rectangle <m>90</m> degrees, the are is then seen as <m>ba</m>. Since rotation doesn’t change the area, we must have <m>ab = ba</m>.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 2.14</term>. <em>Now we would like geometric explanations of the associative laws.</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Explain the associative law for addition using lengths on the number line.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Explain the associative law for multiplication using the fact that the volume of a rectangular prism is the area of its base multiplied by its height (similar to our explanation of the commutative law for multiplication).</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					These rules are most useful in simplifying complex expressions that involve many terms being added together or multiplied.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 2.15</term>. Suppose you have two cans, both are <m>5</m> inches tall, but one has a diameter that it three times that of the other one. Let <m>d</m> denote the diameter of the smaller can, in inches. Suppose we would like to find a simplified expression for the total volume of the two cans in terms of <m>d</m>. First we note the formula for the volume of a cylinder: <m>V=\pi r^2h</m>, where <m>r</m> is the radius and <m>h</m> is the height. Since both cans have a height of <m>5</m> inches, we substitute <m>h = 5</m>. Since <m>r= \frac{d}{2}</m>, the volume of the first can is then given by <m>\pi\cdot\left(\frac{d}{2}\right)^2\cdot 5</m>. Using associativity and commutativity, this simplifies to <me>\mbox{volume of smaller can} = \frac{5}{4}\pi d^2\ \mbox{in}^3.</me> Since the diameter of the larger can is three times that of the smaller can, its radius is <m>\frac{3d}{2}</m>, which makes its volume <me>\mbox{volume of larger can} = \pi\cdot\left(\frac{3d}{2}\right)^2\cdot 5 = \frac{45}{4} \pi d^2\ \mbox{in}^3.</me> Adding them together we have <me>\mbox{Total Volume} = \frac{5}{4}\pi d^2 + \frac{45}{4}\pi d^2 = \frac{25}{2}\pi d^2\ \mbox{in}^3.</me> 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

				<p>
					In the last step of the last example we performed an important type of regrouping known as <em>combining like terms. This is when all the terms with the same algebraic type (same exponents on a variable for example) are combined into a single term by adding together the constants by which they are multiplied. It is important to note that terms can only be combined when the only difference between them is a constant multiplier. For instance, <me>3x^2 + 4\sqrt{x} + 5x^2 - \sqrt{9x} = 8x^2+4\sqrt{x}-3\sqrt{x} = 8x^2+\sqrt{x}.</me> The remaining terms cannot be combined further because one has an exponent of <m>2</m> while the other has an exponent of <m>\frac{1}{2}</m>.</em>
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 2.16</term>. Let’s see another reason unlike terms can’t be combined. Consider the expression <m>4x^3+ 6x</m>. To make it more meaningful, we may think of <m>x</m> as a length with units of meters. Then <m>x^3</m> represents a volume in cubic meters. Because of dimensional considerations, <m>x</m> and <m>x^3</m> cannot be combined in a meaningful way. In order for this expression to make any practical sense when <m>x</m> is in meters, the <m>6</m> needs to be in square meters. However, then the <m>4</m> is dimensionless, while the <m>6</m> represents an area. We cannot add the <m>4</m> and the <m>6</m>, since they represent different units. So thinking of <m>4x^3 + 6x</m> as representing some geometric quantity shows that it cannot be simplified any further.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 2.17</term>. <em>Give a collection of objects (geometric shapes, not necessarily real-world objects) that would have a volume represented by <m>4x^3 + 6x</m>?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 2.18</term>. <em>Decide if the following attempts to combine like terms are correct. If a mistake was made, say what it was and correct it.</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>4xy+7y^2x + 3x^2y +2yx = 6xy + 10x^3y^3</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>(2x^2+1) + (3x+7) + (x^2-8x) = 3x^2-5x+8</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="distributing-expanding-and-factoring">
				<title>Distributing, Expanding, and Factoring</title>

				<p>
					One of the most important rules in constructing equivalent algebraic expressions is the Distributive Law.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>The Distributive Law</term> For any <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> <me>a(b+c) = ab+ac.</me>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

				<p>
					This fact asserts that you can
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					add two lengths, <m>b</m> and <m>c</m>, on the line together, then expand/compress by a factor of <m>a</m>, or
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					expand/contract each of <m>b</m> and <m>c</m> by a factor of <m>a</m>, then add the results together.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					The end result is the same in either case. Many seemingly complex algebraic manipulations boil down to using the distributive law several times and collecting like terms; it’s just that <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> may be some sort of algebraic expressions.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 2.19</term>. Let’s find the expanded form of <m>(x+y)^2</m> using the distributive law. <me>\begin{aligned}
(x+y)^2 &amp; = &amp; (x+y)(x+y)\\
 &amp; = &amp; (x+y)x + (x+y)y  \phantom{www} \mbox{the distributive law}\\
 &amp; = &amp; (x^2+xy) + (xy+y^2) \phantom{wn} \mbox{more distributive law}\\
 &amp; = &amp; x^2+2xy+y^2 \phantom{wwwwwwi} \mbox{combining like terms}\end{aligned}</me>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 2.20</term>. <em>Describe what each term in the second and third lines of the manipulation given above represents geometrically as areas, as in the example in the last section showing <m>(x+y)^2 = x^2+2xy+y^2</m>.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 2.21</term>. Subtraction of quantities in parentheses is often simplified using the distributive law and remembering that subtraction is really just addition of <m>-1</m> times the given quantity. For instance, suppose we want to simplify the expression <me>3x^2 - (4x+2x^2)</me> First, re-write it with addition and <m>-1</m> multiplying the piece in parentheses, then apply the distributive law: <me>\begin{aligned}
3x^2 - (4x+2x^2) &amp; = &amp; 3x^2 + (-1)(4x+2x^2)\\
\ &amp; = &amp; 3x^2+((-1)4x+(-1)2x^2)\\
\ &amp; = &amp; 3x^2-4x-2x^2\\
\ &amp; = &amp; x^2-4x.\end{aligned}</me> With practice, you probably won’t need to write this many steps down. This process is often referred to as <q>distributing a minus sign</q>.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

				<p>
					Now is probably a good time to just get a little practice expanding/distributing and collecting like terms. Just remember the distributive law and you’ll see it’s not that hard.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 2.22</term>. <em>Expand (write as an equivalent expression without parentheses) each of the following expressions and collect like terms:</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>3ab(2a-5b)</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>(2x+1)(3x-4)</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>3x^2(1-x)^3</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>2x-\frac{1}{3}x(5-3x-2x^2)</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					Now we will go backward from expanding/distributing. This process is known as factoring. When we expand an expression, we write it as an equivalent expression that is a sum of simple terms that each only involve multiplication and/or division. To <em>factor an expression means to write it as a product of simple terms. For example, earlier in this chapter we had two expressions for the temperature in <m>^{\circ}</m>C in terms of the temperature in <m>^{\circ}</m>F. The expression <m>C = \frac{5}{9}F - \frac{160}{9}</m> is in expanded form, while <m>C = \frac{5}{9}(F-32)</m> is in factored form. Factored forms of expressions are often useful for solving equations as we’ll see in the next chapter. Factoring isn’t something that can be done in all cases by a single procedure; the following are just a few examples of common factoring methods.</em>
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 2.23</term>. When each term of an expression is divisible by some common factor one can <q>un-distribute</q> that factor. For instance, if we are given the expression <me>12xy+6y^2+3y^3,</me> we can see that each term contains <m>y</m> and <m>3</m> as a factor. This means we can factor <m>3y</m> out of the expression to get the equivalent expression <me>3y(4x+2y+y^2).</me> Note that you can check your answer by applying the distributive law. An interpretation of pulling out a common factor like this is that each term is being stretched/compressed by the same amount, hence we can think of this as a single entity being stretched/compressed, which may be simpler.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 2.24</term>. Expressions of the form <m>ax^2+bx+c</m>, where <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> are constants are known as <term>quadratic</term> expressions in the variable <m>x</m>. Factoring such expressions is a very common and useful algebraic task. It is possible to give a procedure for factoring quadratics, but right now it is best to proceed with examples and practice. For instance, consider the expression <me>12x^2+5x-2.</me> We wish to re-write this expression in the form <me>(rx+p)(sx+q).</me> We note that
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					<m>rs</m> must equal <m>12</m>,
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>pq</m> must equal <m>-2</m>, and
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>rq + ps</m> must equal <m>5</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					Some trial and error leads us to <me>(3x+2)(4x-1),</me> which we may check by expanding. 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 2.25</term>. Any expression of the form <m>a^2-b^2</m> may be factored as <m>(a+b)(a-b)</m> (<m>a</m> and <m>b</m> may represent more complicated expressions in this). One may check this using the distributive law. To see how this factorization works geometrically, consider the following figure with <m>b</m> being thought of as a number smaller than <m>a</m>.<!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

				<p>
					In this figure the entire square has an area of <m>a^2</m> units and the gray shaded area has an area of <m>a^2-b^2</m> units. Each of the smaller shaded rectangles has area <m>b(a-b)</m> and the lower right shaded square has an area of <m>(a-b)(a-b)</m>. Hence the total shaded area is <me>a^2-b^2 = (a-b)(a-b) + 2b(a-b).</me> Now each term has a common factor of <m>(a-b)</m>, hence we may factor it off and simplify by collecting like terms: <me>\begin{aligned}
a^2-b^2 &amp; = &amp; (a-b)(a-b) + 2b(a-b)\\
\ &amp; = &amp; (a-b)(a-b+2b)\\
\ &amp; = &amp; (a-b)(a+b).\end{aligned}</me>
				</p>

				<p>
					One may also see this factorization geometrically by taking the shaded rectangle on top and moving it to the left hand side of the diagram.
				</p>

				<p>
					Now we have a single shaded rectangle whose height is <m>a-b</m> and whose width is <m>a+b</m>, hence the total area is <m>(a-b)(a+b)</m>.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 2.26</term>. <em>Factor each of the following expressions as completely as possible.</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>x^2+5x+6</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>x^4-25x^2y^2</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>4x^2+19x+12</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>y^2-y^4</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>2x^3-16x^2+32x</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>z^4+z^2-2</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 2.27</term>. <em>Think of <m>x</m>, <m>y</m>, and <m>1</m> as positive lengths to use areas of rectangles to explain why <me>6xy + 2y+6x+2 = (3x+1)(2y+2).</me></em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>
		</subsection>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="algebraic-equations">
		<title>Algebraic Equations</title>

		<p>
			An <em>algebraic equation is a pair of algebraic expressions connected by an equals sign. An equation may or may not be true for specific values of the variables. Variable values that make the equation true are known as </em>solutions to the equation. One of the basic tasks in the study of algebra is to find solutions to algebraic equations. In this chapter we will give an overview of some basic techniques of solving equations. We will give more geometric meaning to these solutions when we introduce the concept of the graph of a function in Chapter 4.**
		</p>

		<p>
			Recall that we may think of an algebraic expression as a symbolic representation of some sequence of operations performed on the variable(s). Thus, and algebraic equation indicates that two different processes carried out on the same variable(s) result in the same output. Clearly, different processes typically lead to different results, so solutions to equations are interesting. In our study of algebra, the most fruitful way of thinking of an equation is as a question.
		</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
		<p>
			Algebraic Equation as a Question
		</p>

		<p>
			<em>Algebraic Equation</em> <m>\longrightarrow</m> <em>Question: What values of the variable(s) give the same results when the processes on the right and left are performed?</em> ———————- ——————- ————————————————————————————————————————–
		</p><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
		<p>
			<term>Example 3.1</term>. Consider the equation <me>x^2 = x+x.</me> The left-hand side of the equation multiplies <m>x</m> by itself. The right-hand side adds <m>x</m> to itself. The equation is asking what values of <m>x</m> give same result if you apply these two processes. Upon a little reflection we see that <m>x=2</m> and <m>x=0</m> will work. We may check by substituting these values into the equation and seeing if the resulting numerical equation is true. For <m>x=2</m> we have <me>2^2 = 2+2,</me> which simplifies to <m>4=4</m> (that’s true). If we substitute <m>x=0</m> we have <me>0^2 = 0+0,</me> which is also true. On the other hand, if we substitute <m>x=3</m> the resulting numerical equation is <me>3^2 = 3+3.</me> Since <m>9\neq 6</m>, <m>x=3</m> is not a solution to this equation.
		</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

		<p>
			Since there are infinitely many numbers to check, and equations may be complicated, it would be impossible to proceed by just guessing and checking to find solutions. So for any equation we have the following question:<!-- linebreak -->
		</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
		<p>
			<em>How do we find a solution? </em>
		</p><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

		<p>
			We also see from the example above that equations may have multiple solutions, so we also want to know if we have found all of the solutions. Usually this gets answered on a case by case basis. We will look at some important examples in this chapter.
		</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
		<p>
			<term>Question 3.2</term>.
		</p>

		<p><ol>
			<li>
					<p>
			<em>Find an equation with <m>x=1</m> and <m>x=-1</m> as its only solutions.</em>
		</p>
			</li>

			<li>
					<p>
			<em>For any number <m>a</m>, can you find an equation with <m>x=a</m> and <m>x=-a</m> as its only solutions?</em>
		</p>
			</li>

		</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->


		<subsection xml:id="finding-solutions">
			<title>Finding Solutions</title>


			<subsubsection xml:id="basic-solving">
				<title>Basic Solving</title>

				<p>
					For now, we will consider equations that only involve one variable. Our goal is to find all values of the variable that make the equation true. We ultimately want to get a statement that looks like <me>x=\mbox{some number},</me> so it is often a good first step is to perform operations that will result in all the variables on one side of the equation. Once we have an algebraic expression only on one side of the equation, we hope that we can undo the process represented by that expression to solve for <m>x</m>. Let’s consider a relatively easy example.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 3.3</term>. We wish to solve the equation <me>\sqrt{2x+9} = 5.</me> We don’t need to do any steps to get all the <m>x</m>’s on one side, since they are already there; all we need to do is undo the operations on the left.
				</p>

				<p>
					Now the expression <m>\sqrt{2x+9}</m> means to do the following:
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					Multiply <m>x</m> by <m>2</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					add <m>9</m> to <term>S1</term>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					take the square root of <term>S2</term>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					We can solve the equation by systematically undoing each of these steps, starting with <term>S3</term>. So we do the following:
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					square both sides to get <me>2x+9 = 25.</me>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					subtract <m>9</m> to get <me>2x = 16.</me>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					divide by <m>2</m> to get <me>x=8.</me>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					You should substitute <m>x=8</m> into the original equation to check that it is a solution. 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

				<p>
					Notice that after each step in solving an equation you are left with another equation. We hope that the new equation will be easier to solve after each step. The critical thing is that each new equation must be <em>equivalent the previous one in the sense that it has the same solutions. The manipulations that one can do to equations that result in equivalent equations are as follows:</em>
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					Replace an algebraic expression with an equivalent algebraic expression. This usually takes the form of simplifying the expression one side of the equation in order to make solving easier.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Apply an operation to both sides of the equation. This is what you do when you
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					apply the same operation to both sides of an equation, and
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					undo operations in order to solve for the variable.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					Often, when we apply the same operation to both sides of an equation, this takes the form of <q>moving from one side to the other</q>. What is really happening is undoing an operation on one side and applying the same inverse operation on the other.
				</p>

				<p>
					To eliminate confusion, each time we write down an equivalent equation from a given equation, we will use the symbol <m>\longleftrightarrow</m> or <m>\updownarrow</m> to separate them. Interpret this symbol as meaning <q>this equation is true exactly when that equation is true</q>.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 3.4</term>. <em>Write down exactly was done at each step in the following process to solve <me>\frac{10}{x+5} = 5.</me> <me>\begin{aligned}
\frac{10}{x+5} &amp; = &amp; 5\\
\ &amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
\frac{1}{x+5} &amp; =  &amp; \frac{1}{2}\\
\ &amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
x+5 &amp; = &amp; 2\\
\ &amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
x &amp; = &amp; -3.\end{aligned}</me></em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 3.5</term>. We wish to solve the equation <me>\frac{3x}{x-5} = 2.</me> This equation already has all of the <m>x</m>’s on one side of the equation, but the expression on the left-hand side doesn’t represent a process that seems to be easily undone. Our first step is to <q>clear the denominator</q> from the left-hand side. While this seems to initially take us backwards, the resulting equation is more easily solved. <me>\begin{aligned}
\frac{3x}{x-5} &amp; = &amp; 2\\
\ &amp; \updownarrow &amp; (\mbox{multiply both sides by\ } x-5)\\
3x &amp; = &amp; 2(x-5)\\
\ &amp; \updownarrow &amp; (\mbox{distribute})\\
3x &amp; = &amp; 2x-10\\
\ &amp; \updownarrow &amp; (\mbox{move the\ } 2x)\\
x &amp; = &amp; -10.\end{aligned}</me> Just to check, we can substitute into the original equation and see that <m>\frac{3(-10)}{-10-5} = 2</m>. 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

				<p>
					Clearly, solving equations can be rather complicated. It would be impossible to write down an example of every solution method. In fact, there are many equations for which not algebraic methods are effective for solving. However, if you just apply the manipulations given above to get equivalent equations, you can solve many of the equations you might encounter. Becoming proficient will require plenty of thoughtful practice.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 3.6</term>. <em>Solve the following equations for the indicated variable.</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>7+2x = 2+3(x+1)</m>. Solve for <m>x</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>1-(x-7) = 2x+4</m>. Solve for <m>x</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>4(t-1)^2 = 16</m>. Solve for <m>t</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>\frac{2p-1}{3-4p} = 8</m>. Solve for <m>p</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>\frac{1}{x} + \frac{2}{x+1} = 0</m>. Solve for <m>x</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>\frac{1}{2x+7} = \frac{3}{x-1}</m>. Solve for <m>x</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>|2x-1| = 5</m>. Solve for <m>x</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="solutions-from-factoring">
				<title>Solutions from Factoring</title>

				<p>
					In Chapter 1 we observed that <m>0a=0</m> for any real number <m>a</m>. In this section (and frequently from now on) we will use the following important fact:
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>Zero Factors Theorem</term><!-- linebreak -->If <m>ab=0</m>, then either <m>a=0</m> or <m>b=0</m>.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

				<p>
					This is a very powerful fact for solving equations. Using this, if we can break a complicated expression into a product of simpler expressions, then the complicated expression is zero only if one of the simpler expressions is zero. This is the main reason we factor algebraic expressions.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 3.7</term>. Earlier we solved the equation <me>x^2 = 2x</me> by inspection. Now we can solve it by factoring. Our first step is to put this equation in the form <me>\mbox{some algebraic expression}=0</me> so that we may apply the Zero Factors Theorem after factoring the expression on the left-hand side. We do this by subtracting the <m>2x</m> over to the left-hand side, then proceeding as follows: <me>\begin{aligned}
x^2 &amp; = &amp; 2x\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; (\mbox{subtract})\\
x^2-2x &amp; = &amp; 0\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; (\mbox{factor}) \\
x(x-2) &amp; = &amp; 0.\end{aligned}</me> Now we use the Zero Factors Theorem; either <m>x=0</m> or <m>x-2 = 0</m>. Hence our solutions are <m>x=0</m> and <m>x=2</m>.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

				<p>
					Note that the Zero Factors Theorem only works if the product is equal to zero.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 3.8</term>. <em>Solve each of the following equations by factoring:</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>2x^2+5x = 0</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>x^2+5x = 6</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>x^2-4x+3 = 8</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>6x^2-x-1 = 0</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>4x^2+7x+1 = 3</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					Sometimes it is not obvious that factoring will be helpful to solve an equation. However, after a little manipulation we see that many equations can be solved using factoring as the critical step.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 3.9</term>. We wish to solve <me>\frac{2}{x} - \frac{2}{x-3} = 3.</me> It is not obvious that this would lend itself to factoring. All we can do is proceed with manipulations we know are allowed, and hopefully we reach a point where we can solve. <me>\begin{aligned}
\frac{2}{x} - \frac{2}{x-3} &amp; = &amp; 3\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; (\mbox{combine fractions on left})\\
\frac{2(x-3)-2x}{x(x-3)} &amp; = &amp; 3\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; (\mbox{simplify numerator on left})\\
\frac{-6}{x(x-3)} &amp; = &amp; 3\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; (\mbox{clear the denominator})\\
-6 &amp; = &amp; 3x(x-3)\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; (\mbox{distribute and rearrange the equation}\\
3x^2-9x + 6 &amp; = &amp; 0\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; (\mbox{factor})\\
3(x-1)(x-2) &amp; = &amp; 0.\end{aligned}</me> Now, by the zero Factors Theorem, we have the solution <m>x=1</m> and <m>x=2</m>. 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 3.10</term>. <em>solve the following equations:</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>x+\frac{1}{x} = 2</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>x^2-x^3+2x = 0</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>\frac{3}{z-2} - \frac{12}{z^2-4} = 1</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>
		</subsection>

		<subsection xml:id="solving-systems-of-equations">
			<title>Solving Systems of Equations</title>

			<p>
				What if we need to solve an equation with more than one variable? For instance, consider the equation <me>x+3y  = 0.</me> For such an equation, a solution is a <em>pair of numbers, an <m>x</m>-value and a <m>y</m>-value, that make the equation true when they are simultaneously plugged in. We see that if <m>y=1</m>, then <m>x=-3</m> makes the equation true. If <m>y=2</m>, then the correct value for <m>x</m> is <m>-6</m>. Clearly we could go on like this, obtaining a different value of <m>x</m> for any given value of <m>y</m>. There is no way for us to say that this equation has a single solution; it has infinitely many. Often in problems the number of solutions is narrowed down by having more equations, which we call a </em>system of equations. For instance, we may consider the system <me>\begin{aligned}
x+3y &amp; = &amp; 0\\
2x-y &amp; = &amp; 1.\end{aligned}</me> A solution to this system of two equations is again a pair of numbers, one for each variable, that make all the equations true at the same time. For instance <m>x=-3</m> and <m>y=1</m> is  a solution to this system; this pair makes the first equation true, but not the second. The pair <m>x=1</m> and <m>y=1</m> makes the second equation true, but not the first, so this is also not a solution to the system.**
			</p>

			<p>
				So how do we find solutions to systems? The most flexible way of solving systems of equations is known as the method of substitution.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
			<p>
				<term>Substitution to Solve Systems of Equations</term><!-- linebreak -->To solve a system of equations
			</p>

			<p><ul>
				<li>
							<p>
				Pick an equation and solve it for one of the variables in terms of the others.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				Substitute the expression from the step above into the remaining equations.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				Now the remaining equations form a system with one fewer variables and one fewer equations.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				Repeat until you just have one equation and one variable that you can solve for.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				Finally, back substitute the value you found to know the other variables.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ul></p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

			<p>
				Let’s see this at work with the system given above. Using the first equation, we can solve for <m>x</m> in terms of <m>y</m> as follows: <me>\begin{aligned}
x+3y &amp; = &amp; 0\\
\ &amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
x &amp; = &amp; -3y.\end{aligned}</me> Now we substitute <m>-3y</m> every time we see an <m>x</m> in the second equation and solve for <m>y</m>: <me>\begin{aligned}
2(-3y) - y &amp; = &amp; 1\\
\ &amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
-7y &amp; = &amp; 1\\
\ &amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
y &amp; = &amp; -\frac{1}{7}.\end{aligned}</me> Now we have <m>y=-\frac{1}{7}</m>, hence <m>x = -3y = \frac{3}{7}</m>. We can now check to make sure we obtained a correct solution by plugging these values into the original system: <me>\begin{aligned}
\frac{3}{7} +3\left(\frac{-1}{7}\right) &amp; = &amp; \frac{3}{7}-\frac{3}{7} = 0 \phantom{s} \tikz\fill[scale=0.4](0,.35) -- (.25,0) -- (1,.7) -- (.25,.15) -- cycle;\\
2\left(\frac{3}{7}\right) - \frac{-1}{7} &amp; = &amp; \frac{6}{7}+\frac{1}{7} = 1
\phantom{s} \tikz\fill[scale=0.4](0,.35) -- (.25,0) -- (1,.7) -- (.25,.15) -- cycle;.\end{aligned}</me>
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 3.11</term>. <em>Solve the following systems of equations:</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em><me>\begin{aligned}
x^2y &amp; = &amp; 1\\
32xy^2 &amp; = &amp; x^2\end{aligned}</me></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><me>\begin{aligned}
x^2+y^2 &amp; = &amp; 25\\
3x-4y &amp; = &amp; 0\end{aligned}</me></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><me>\begin{aligned}
ab^3 &amp; = &amp; 2\\
ab^{-1} &amp; = &amp; 8\end{aligned}</me></em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 3.12</term>. <em>An exam has thirty questions. The professor subtracts eight points for each incorrect answer and adds seven points for each correct answer. If a student ends up receiving zero points, how many questions were answered correctly? <term>Hint:</term> Let <m>C</m> denote the number of correct answers and <m>I</m> denote the number of incorrect answers and set up a system of equations.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 3.13</term>. <em>Typically you need as many equations as variables in order to not have infinitely many solutions. Use substitution to solve the following system of three equations and three unknowns: <me>\begin{aligned}
2x+3y +z &amp; = &amp; 1\\
x &amp; = &amp; 3y\\
x+y &amp; = z.\end{aligned}</me></em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
			<p>
				<term>Example 3.14</term>. Sometimes we need to solve a system of equations in order to manipulate an expression into another form. For instance, an important type of manipulation in Calculus and Differential Equations is known as the <em>Partial Fraction Decomposition</em>. In this manipulation, we take a single fraction and split it as a sum of pieces with simpler, but different, denominators. For instance, let’s write <me>\frac{4}{(x-1)(x+2)}</me> in the form <me>\frac{A}{x-1} + \frac{B}{x+2}</me> for some numbers <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>. These two expressions are to be equivalent for all values of <m>x</m>, we need to solve for <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>. To do this, set the expressions equal to one another and do some manipulations. <me>\begin{aligned}
\frac{A}{x-1} + \frac{B}{x+2} &amp; = &amp; \frac{4}{(x-1)(x+2)}\\
\ &amp; \updownarrow &amp; (\mbox{combine fractions on left})\\
\frac{A(x+2) + B(x-1)}{(x-1)(x+2)} &amp; = &amp; \frac{4}{(x-1)(x+2)}\\
\ &amp; \updownarrow &amp; (\mbox{simplify the expression on the left})\\
\frac{(A+B)x + 2A -B}{(x-1)(x+2)} &amp; = &amp; \frac{4}{(x-1)(x+2)}.\end{aligned}</me> Now we set the numerators equal: <me>(A+B)x + 2A-B = 4.</me> Note that like terms are grouped on both sides. Since there are zero <m>x</m>’s on the right, we must have <m>A+B = 0</m>. Since <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> are numbers, we must have <m>2A-B = 4</m>. Thus we have a system of equations <me>\begin{aligned}
A+B &amp; = &amp; 0\\
2A-B &amp; = &amp; 4.\end{aligned}</me> Using the first equation we have <m>B = -A</m>. Substituting into the second equation we see <m>3A = 4</m>. Hence, <m>A = \frac{4}{3}</m> and <m>B=-\frac{4}{3}</m>.
			</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 3.15</term>. <em>Check that <me>\frac{4}{3(x-1)} - \frac{4}{3(x+2)} = \frac{4}{(x-1)(x+2)}.</me></em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 3.16</term>. <em>Solve for <m>h</m> and <m>k</m> to put the expression <me>x^2+2x+5</me> in the form <me>(x-h)^2+k.</me></em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

		</subsection>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="introduction-to-functions">
		<title>Introduction to Functions</title>

		<p>
			The concept of one variable being a function of another is central to the study of most modern pure and applied mathematics. The idea of a function allows us to bring together all the equivalent forms of an expression and solving algebraic equations under one unifying concept. It also provides us with new ways of visualizing algebraic processes via graphs of functions. In this chapter we will explore the different ways of thinking about functions.
		</p>


		<subsection xml:id="inputs-and-outputs">
			<title>Inputs and Outputs</title>

			<p>
				A <em>function is a relation between two variables <m>x</m> (the input) and <m>y</m> (the output) where each input is related to only one output (the variables <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are generic, different letters may be used). Because this is an algebra course, most such relations will be defined with an algebraic equation with <m>y</m> alone on one side and some algebraic expression involving <m>x</m> on the other. We use letters to name functions; often <m>f</m> is used if we are giving a name to a function when <m>f</m> isn’t already in use elsewhere in the problem. If <m>y</m> is related to <m>x</m> by the function <m>f</m> we write <me>y = f(x).</me> We read this as <q><m>y</m> equals <m>f</m> of <m>x</m></q>.</em>
			</p>


			<subsubsection xml:id="evaluating-functions-and-using-function-notation">
				<title>Evaluating Functions and Using Function Notation</title>

				<p>
					For most people, more needs to be said about how to think about functions and use function notation than was given above. Suppose we are given the definition of a function as <me>y = f(x) = \mbox{some expression involving } x.</me> From a symbolic point of view we may think of <m>f</m> as a certain type of shorthand.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
				<p>
					Function Notation as Shorthand
				</p>

				<p>
					<em>Function: <m>y = f(x)</m></em> <m>\longrightarrow</m> <em><m>f(x)</m> is a compact way of writing what may be a complicated algebraic expression. </em> ———————— ——————- —————————————————————————————
				</p><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

				<p>
					<term>Remark:</term> Not all functions are defined using algebraic expressions. For instance trigonometric functions can only be defined using geometry and/or concepts from calculus. However, for our purposes right now, this is an effective way to think about functions.
				</p>

				<p>
					Because we can think of algebraic expressions as processes carried out on variables, we may also think of a function as a process performed on <m>x</m>, resulting in <m>y</m>. Equipped with the idea of equivalence of algebraic expressions, we may think of a function <m>f</m> in a more conceptual way. We can think of <m>f</m> as a factory that takes <m>x</m>’s as raw ingredients and makes specific <m>y</m>’s. Equivalence of the defining expressions for <m>f</m> can be thought of as rearranging the factory, but ultimately leaving the product being produced unchanged.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
				<p>
					Function as <q><m>y</m> factory</q>
				</p>

				<p>
					<em>Function: <m>y = f(x)</m></em> <m>\longrightarrow</m> <em><m>f</m> is the set of all processes that result in the same outputs (<m>y</m>’s) as the expression <m>f(x)</m>. In other words, any expression that is equivalent to <m>f(x)</m> defines the same function, so we say it is also <m>f(x)</m>. </em> ———————— ——————- ————————————————————————————————————————————————————————————————————————–
				</p><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

				<p>
					In applications, we usually think of the input as a variable we control and the output as one that results from a process. For this reason we call the input the <em>independent variable and the output the </em>dependent variable.**
				</p>

				<p>
					Given a function, you evaluate by plugging in the input for <m>x</m>. The result is the value of <m>y</m> corresponding to that <m>x</m>-value.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 4.1</term>. Define the function <m>f</m> by <m>y = f(x) = 3x^2-1</m>. Evaluate the following:
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<m>f(2)</m>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>f(x+1)</m>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>2f(x) -1</m>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p>

				<p>
					
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					The function <m>f(x)</m> tells us to take any input <m>x</m> and do the following: square the input <m>x</m>; then multiply by <m>3</m>; then subtract <m>1</m>. If <m>x=2</m>, we will get: <m>2^2 = 4</m>; then multiply by <m>3</m> to get <m>12</m>; then subtract <m>1</m> to get <m>11</m>. So <m>f(2) = 3\cdot 2^2 -1 = 11</m>. The output of <m>f</m> when <m>x=2</m> is <m>y = 11</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					This time, we think of <m>x+1</m> as our input, a quantity that must be evaluated before <m>f</m> is applied, so we enclose it in parentheses in the evaluation. Then we apply the steps and simplify by expanding and collecting like terms. <me>\begin{aligned}
f(x+1) &amp; = &amp; 3(x+1)^2 - 1\\
 &amp; = &amp; 3(x^2+2x+1) - 1   \phantom{ww} \textup{ square } (x+1) \\
 &amp; = &amp; 3x^2+6x +3 - 1   \phantom{www} \textup{ multiply by  } 3 \\
  &amp; = &amp; 3x^2+6x + 2.   \phantom{wwwww} \textup{ subtract } 1 \\\end{aligned}</me> Note that <m>f(x+1)</m> is not the same function as <m>f(x)</m>; for any <m>x</m>-value, <m>f(x+1)</m> says that we add <m>1</m> to <m>x</m> and then apply all the steps of <m>f</m>. This can be used to define another function, say <m>y = g(x) = f(x+1)</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					In this part we first apply <m>f</m> to <m>x</m>, and then do two additional steps: multiply by <m>2</m> and then subtract <m>1</m>. Here we think of <m>f(x)</m> as being enclosed in parentheses: <me>\begin{aligned}
2f(x) - 1 &amp; = &amp; 2(3x^2-1) -1   \phantom{ww} \textup{ apply  } f \textup{ to } x \\
 &amp; = &amp; 6x^2-2-1   \phantom{wwww} \textup{ multiply by  } 2 \\ 
  &amp; = &amp; 6x^2-3.   \phantom{wwwwww} \textup{ subtract   } 1\\\end{aligned}</me>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 4.2</term>. <em>Let <m>f(x) = \frac12 x^2</m>. Find simplified expressions for each of the following, and describe the steps they represent.</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>f(3x+2)</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>3f(x) + 2</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 4.3</term>. <em>Let <m>f(x) = x^2-4x+5</m> and <m>g(x) = x^2+1</m>. Define another function <m>h(x)</m> by saying <m>h(x) = g(x-2)</m>. Use algebra to show that <m>h(x)</m> is actually the same function as <m>f(x)</m>.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					<term>Domain</term> One important question about any given function is, "What are its allowable inputs?" Using the factory analogy, what raw ingredients can that factory work with? This set of numbers is called the <em>domain of the function. One of the primary goals of Calculus is to investigate how functions behave at inputs <q>at the boundary</q> of the domain. In order to determine the domain of a function, it is good to read through it as a sequence of procedures, then decide if anything is not allowed at any point in that process. Those values of <m>x</m> that force us into an operation that is not allowed with normal arithmetic are the values of <m>x</m> that are  in the domain. For functions defined algebraically, the main things that are not allowed are:</em>
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					division by zero, and
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					even roots of negative numbers.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 4.4</term>. Suppose we have the function <m>f(x) = \sqrt{x-2}</m>. We want to find the domain. We see that there is a square root, and so we cannot put a negative value under the square root sign; thus <m>x-2</m> must be nonnegative. Set <m>x-2 \geq 0</m>, we can solve this to find <m>x \geq 2</m>. Thus the domain is <m>[2, \infty)</m>.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 4.5</term>. Suppose we wish to find the domain of <me>f(x) = \frac{\sqrt{x^2-1}}{2x+3}.</me> This function has two main parts:
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					Takes the square root of <m>x^2-1</m>, then
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Divide <term>Part 1</term> by <m>2x+3</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p>

				<p>
					We can look at each part separately to determine the domain. For <term>Part 1</term>, we can certainly square any <m>x</m>, and subtract <m>1</m>. It is the square root that will be a problem. We need to have <m>x^2-1 \geq 0</m>. If <m>x</m> is between <m>-1</m> and <m>1</m>, then <m>x^2</m> is less than <m>1</m>, so <m>x^2-1</m> is negative. So <m>-1&lt;x&lt;1</m> must be excluded from the domain since these values would force us to take the square root of a negative number. For <term>Part 2</term>, we are not allowed to divide by zero. We will find where <m>2x+3</m> is zero and exclude it: <m>x=-\frac{3}{2}</m>. Thus the domain is all <m>x</m> with <m>x\leq -1</m> or <m>x\geq 1</m>, except for <m>x=-\frac{3}{2}</m>. In interval notation, this would be written as <me>\left(-\infty,-\frac{3}{2}\right)\bigcup \left(-\frac{3}{2},-1\right] \bigcup \left[1,\infty\right).</me> 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 4.6</term>. <em>Find the domain of each of the following functions. <term>Carefully explain how you found it, as illustrated in the previous example.</term> Express your answer using inequalities and words, as well as using interval notation (see refresher after the question if you don’t remember interval notation).</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>f(x) = \sqrt{3x + 1-x}</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>g(x) = \dfrac{1}{x^2-x-6}</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>h(x) = \dfrac{1}{\sqrt{x^2-x-6}}</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>k(x) = f(x+1)</m>, where <m>f</m> is the function defined in part (a)</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>Interval Notation</term><!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

				<table>
					<caption></caption>
					<tabular>
					<row header="yes">
						<cell halign="left">Verbal Description</cell>
						<cell halign="left">Inequalities Describing <m>x</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left">Interval(s) Containing <m>x</m></cell>
					</row>
					<row class="odd">
						<cell halign="left"><m>x</m> is greater than <m>a</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>x&gt;a</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>(a,\infty)</m></cell>
					</row>
					<row class="even">
						<cell halign="left"><m>x</m> is greater than or equal to <m>a</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>x\geq a</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>[a,\infty)</m></cell>
					</row>
					<row class="odd">
						<cell halign="left"><m>x</m> is less than <m>a</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>x&lt;a</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>(-\infty,a)</m></cell>
					</row>
					<row class="even">
						<cell halign="left"><m>x</m> is less than or equal to <m>a</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>x\leq a</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>(-\infty,a]</m></cell>
					</row>
					<row class="odd">
						<cell halign="left"><m>x</m> is greater than (or equal to) <m>a</m> and less than (or equal to) <m>b</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>a&lt;(\leq) x &lt;(\leq) b</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>(a,b),(a,b],[a,b)</m>, or <m>[a,b]</m>, depending on strictness</cell>
					</row>
					<row class="even">
						<cell halign="left"><m>x</m> is greater than (or equal to) <m>b</m> or less than (or equal to) <m>a</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>x&gt;(\geq) b</m> or <m>x&lt;(\leq) a</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>(-\infty,a)\bigcup(b,\infty)</m>, with <m>(,),[,</m> or <m>]</m> used at <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, depending on strictness.</cell>
					</row>
					</tabular>
				</table><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 4.7</term>. <em>Sometimes the context of a problem restricts the domain of a function when the algebra may not. For instance, suppose a farmer wants to fence off a rectangular area with three sides of a rectangle, using a river as the fourth side. He has 100 yards of fence to use. Let <m>x</m> denote the length of the side of the rectangle parallel to the river. Find a formula for the function <m>A(x)</m> that gives the area as a function of <m>x</m>. What is the domain of this function based on the formula and what is it based on the context of the problem?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="solving-equations-involving-functions">
				<title>Solving Equations Involving Functions</title>

				<p>
					In solving algebraic equations, perhaps the most straightforward ones to solve are of the form <me>(\mbox{algebraic expression}) = \mbox{a number},</me> where the algebraic expression on the left represents a process applied to a variable that we reverse to solve. Equipped with the idea of functions, we now can simply think of these in the form <me>f(x) = \mbox{a number}.</me> More complicated equations typically have the form <me>f(x) = g(x),</me> where <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> are different functions. When we think of function notation as shorthand for specified algebraic expressions, solving equations involving functions is not different than solving equations as we have before now.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 4.8</term>. Let <m>f(x) = x^2-3x</m> and <m>g(x) = 2x-4</m>. Let’s solve the following equations;
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<m>g(x) = 8</m>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>f(x) = g(x)</m>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>f(x+1) = g(x)</m>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p>

				<p>
					
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					. For (a) we use the fact that <m>g(x) = 2x-4</m>, so we get the following: <me>\begin{aligned}
2x-4 &amp; = &amp; 8\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp;\\
2x&amp; = &amp; 12\\ 
&amp; \updownarrow &amp;\\
x&amp; =&amp; 6.\end{aligned}</me>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					For (b), we use <m>f(x) = x^2-3x</m> and <m>g(x) = 2x+4</m>. Then we factor to solve: <me>\begin{aligned}
x^2 - 3x  &amp; = &amp; 2x-4\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
x^2-5x+4 &amp; = &amp; 0\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
(x-4)(x-1) &amp; = &amp; 0\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
x=4 &amp; \mbox{or} &amp; x=1.\end{aligned}</me>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					For (c), we need to figure out what <m>f(x+1)</m> means. Now <m>f</m> is the function that takes any input, squares it, then multiplies a new copy of it by three, then finds the difference. In this case, our input is the quantity <m>(x+1)</m>. So we to is substitute <m>(x+1)</m> each time we see and <m>x</m> in the expression for <m>f(x)</m> and set it equal to <m>g(x)</m>: <me>\begin{aligned}
(x+1)^2 - 3(x+1) &amp; = &amp; 2x-4\\ 
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \mbox{expand, group like terms on one side}\\
x^2-3x+2 &amp; = &amp; 0\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
(x-1)(x-2) &amp; = &amp; 0\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
x=1 &amp; \mbox{or} &amp; x=2.\end{aligned}</me>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p>

				<p>
					
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 4.9</term>. <em>Let <m>f(x) = x-1</m>, and <m>g(x) = (x-3)^2</m>. Solve each of the following equations:</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>f(x) = 2</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>f(x) = 2x-6</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>f(x) = g(x)</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 4.10</term>. <em>Let <m>f(x) = \dfrac{x}{3x+7}</m>. Solve the following equations, if possible. If it is impossible to solve, explain why.</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>f(x) = 1</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>f(x) = x</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>f(x) = \frac{1}{3}</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					As seen in part (c) of the last question, some numbers may not appear as outputs of a given function. The set of numbers that <em>do appear as outputs of a given function is called the </em>range of the function. Another way to say what the range of <m>f</m> is, is that it is the set of <m>y</m> such that there is a solution to the equation <m>y=f(x)</m>. Finding the range of a function is generally a more difficult task than finding its domain; being able to find the maximum and/or minimum possible outputs of a given function is one of the main achievements of Calculus. However, in many cases we can determine the range of an algebraically defined function by some combination of the following:**
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					Determine what arithmetic operations the function applies to its input, and think about what the possible results could be.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Solve the general equation <m>y=f(x)</m> for <m>x</m>, if possible. The result will be an expression involving <m>y</m>; the range of <m>f</m> will be the <m>y</m>-values that can be substituted into this expression.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 4.11</term>. Find the range of the following functions:
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<m>f(x) = \dfrac{x}{3x+7}</m>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>g(x) = -(x-3)^2 + 4</m>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>h(x) = 2x+1</m>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>k(x) = 2x+1 + \sqrt{x-1}</m>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p>

				<p>
					
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					This is the function from Question 4.10. If we solve the equation <me>y = \frac{x}{3x+7}</me> for <m>x</m>, we have the general solution <me>x = \frac{7y}{1-3y}.</me> The only <m>y</m>-value that cannot be substituted into this is <m>y=\frac{1}{3}</m>. Thus, the range of <m>f</m> is all real numbers except <m>\frac{1}{3}</m>. Using inequalities, we would write <m>y&lt;\frac{1}{3}</m> or <m>y&gt;\frac{1}{3}</m>. In interval notation, it would be written as <m>\left(-\infty,\frac{1}{3}\right)\bigcup\left(\frac{1}{3},\infty\right)</m>.
				</p>

				<p>
					<term>Remark:</term> For problems involving domain and range, using inequalities to describe the domain and range may be preferable to interval notation. This is because inequalities make explicit which variables are elements of the domain (the input variable) and the range (the output variable).
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					For this problem, we can use our understanding of the defining expression to find the range. The function <m>g</m> takes <m>x</m> and subtracts three from it, squares the result, multiplies that by <m>-1</m>, and finally adds four. Noting that squares are never negative, <m>-(x-3)^2</m> will never be positive. This means no positive number is ever added to four. A little thought shows that any number less than or equal to four is an output of this function. So the range is <m>y\leq 4</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Algebraically solving <m>y=h(x)</m> for <m>x</m> yields <m>x = \frac{y-1}{2}</m>. No values of <m>y</m> make the right-hand side of this equation undefined, so the range is <m>-\infty &lt; y &lt; \infty</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					For this problem, we must note the domain of the function before determining the range. Because of the inclusion of the <m>\sqrt{x-1}</m> term, the domain of <m>k</m> is <m>x\geq 1</m>. Possible outputs of <m>2x+1</m> over this domain are all numbers greater than or equal to three. Putting this together with the possible outputs of the expression <m>\sqrt{x-1}</m>, we see the range of <m>k</m> is <m>y\geq 3</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p>

				<p>
					
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 4.12</term>. <em>Determine the domain and range of the following functions. Explain your answers carefully as in the last example.</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>f(x) = -2(x-4)^2+3</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>g(x) = \dfrac{1}{\sqrt{x-4}}</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>
		</subsection>

		<subsection xml:id="graphs-of-functions">
			<title>Graphs of Functions</title>

			<p>
				Until now, our development has regarded a function as only slightly different than an algebraic expression. Algebraic expressions represent processes applied to their variables (the inputs), just like functions. The function concept blends this idea with solving equations by considering the evaluation result (the output) as a key piece; the output is a number that the function can equal for some input, which may be solved for. The graph of a function takes us a step further, so that we may see the totality of all inputs and outputs of the function as a single object, the graph of the function.
			</p>

			<p>
				The graph of a general function of the form <m>y = f(x)</m> is a set of points in the <m>xy</m>-plane (or whatever the input and output variables happen to be). To plot a single point <m>(a,b)</m> in the <m>xy</m>-plane, we move a distance of <m>a</m> along the <m>x</m>-axis (the horizontal axis), then a vertical distance <m>b</m> from there (the vertical axis is the <m>y</m>-axis as in the following figure:
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
			<p>
				<term>The Graph of a Function</term><!-- linebreak -->The graph of <m>y = f(x)</m> is the set of all points in the <m>xy</m>-plane that satisfy the equation <m>y=f(x)</m>. Stated another way we have the following equivalence: <me>(a,b)\ \mbox{is on the graph of\ }\\ y=f(x)\ \mbox{if and only if}\ b = f(a).</me>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

			<p>
				To sketch the graph of a function, one starts by finding a reasonable number of points on the graph, often putting them in an input-output table, then plotting them in the plane. When a general pattern is evident, we usually fill in between the plotted points with a smooth curve.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
			<p>
				<term>Example 4.13</term>. Consider the function <m>y = f(x) = x^2-4</m>. First, we will find some pairs of points on the graph by evaluating the function for some <m>x</m>-values and recording the results in a table:<!-- linebreak -->
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
			<table>
				<caption></caption>
				<tabular>
				<row header="yes">
					<cell halign="center"><m>x</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>-3</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>-2</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>-1</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>0</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>1</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>2</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>3</m></cell>
				</row>
				<row class="odd">
					<cell halign="center"><m>y = f(x) = x^2-4</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>5</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>0</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>-3</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>-4</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>-3</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>0</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>5</m></cell>
				</row>
				</tabular>
			</table><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

			<p>
				Then we plot the points according to the table and fill in a curve:<!-- linebreak -->
			</p>

			<p>
				
			</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 4.14</term>. <em>On your own paper, carefully graph the following functions by plotting at least six points.</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>f(x) = 3x-2</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>g(x) = \sqrt{x}</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>h(x) = \dfrac{1}{x}</m> (Be sure to plot several points with <m>x</m> values between <m>-1</m> and <m>1</m>.)</em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			<p>
				Equipped with graphs of functions, we may now catalog graphical interpretations of many of the skills and concepts we have encountered so far.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
			<p>
				<term>Graphical Interpretations of Algebraic Skills with Functions</term>
			</p>

			<p><ul>
				<li>
							<p>
				To evaluate a function at some value <m>x=a</m>, move to the <m>a</m> position on the horizontal axis and then find the vertical coordinate on the graph above or below that point.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				To solve an equation of the form <m>f(x) = b</m>, find the <m>x</m>-coordinates of all points on the graph whose <m>y</m>-coordinate is <m>b</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				To solve an equation of the form <m>f(x) = g(x)</m>, we are asking for the input values such that <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> give the same output. Hence we must find the <m>x</m>-coordinates of all points of intersection between the graphs of <m>f</m> and <m>g</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				The domain of a function is the set of <m>x</m>-coordinates of all points on the graph. This may be visualized as the set of values on the horizontal axis that lie above or below the graph of the function.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				The range of a function is the set of <m>y</m>-coordinates of all points on the graph. This may be visualized as the set of values on the vertical axis that lie to the left or right of the graph of the function.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ul></p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 4.15</term>. <em>Consider the graph of the function shown below (the  graph is shown).<!-- linebreak --></em>
			</p>

			<p>
				<em>Find each of the following, approximate if necessary:</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em>The domain of <m>f</m>.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>The range of <m>f</m>.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>f(1)</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>All solutions to the equation <m>f(x) = 1</m>.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em>All solutions to the equation <m>f(x) = x+1</m>.</em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

		</subsection>

		<subsection xml:id="composite-and-inverse-functions">
			<title>Composite and Inverse Functions</title>

			<p>
				On many occasions we have broken down algebraic expressions as a sequence of steps, often determined by order of operations. Now that we have the concept of a function, we may view this breaking down in terms of <em>function composition or decomposition. Simply put, we may view each step in a sequence of operation defining a function as its own function. For instance, consider the function <m>h</m> defined by the algebraic expression in the first example of Chapter 2. This function is <me>y =  h(x) = (3x+1)^2-2.</me> When we broke down that expression, we noted that it takes <m>x</m> and does the following:</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				multiplies <m>x</m> by <m>3</m>,
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				adds one to <term>S1</term>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				squares <term>S3</term>, and finally
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				subtracts two from <term>S4</term>,
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p>

			<p>
				to give us an output <m>y</m>. Now, we can think about this as two processes, one that does the first two steps <term>S1</term> and <term>S2</term>, and one that does the last two steps <term>S3</term> and <term>S4</term>. For the first two steps, we can use the function <me>u = g(x) = 3x+1.</me> The last two steps then are performed on the output of <m>g</m> by another function <me>y = f(u) = u^2-2.</me> Symbolically, we substitute the expression for <m>g(x)</m> into <m>f(u)</m> for <m>u</m> to get our expression for <m>h(x)</m>: <me>y = h(x) = f(g(x)).</me> In general, a new function <m>h</m> constructed out of a pair of functions <m>g</m> and <m>f</m> is called the <em>composition of <m>f</m> with <m>g</m>. The function <m>g</m> is referred to as the </em>inside function and <m>f</m> is referred to as the <em>outside function. The inputs of the composition are the inputs of the inside function and the outputs are the outputs of the outside function.</em>**
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 4.16</term>. <em>If <m>u = f(x) = 2+3x</m> and <m>x=g(u) = 5u+1</m>, then both <m>f(g(u))</m> and <m>g(f(x))</m> make sense. Find them. Are they the same?</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
			<p>
				<term>Example 4.17</term>. Often we decompose functions by finding inside and outside functions that are easier to work with than the composite. One task that we do this for is finding domains and ranges of composites. For instance, consider the function <me>y = \sqrt{x^2-1}.</me> This may be decomposed as <m>f(g(x))</m> where <m>u = g(x) = x^2-1</m> and <m>y=f(u) = \sqrt{u}</m>. The domain of the composite is those inputs of the inside function that, when the inside function is applied, result in legal inputs of the outside function. The domain of the outside function is <m>u\geq 0</m>, hence we must find <m>x</m>’s such that the output of <m>x^2-1</m> is non-negative. This occurs only if <m>x\geq 1</m> or <m>x\leq -1</m> as numbers between <m>-1</m> and <m>1</m> will square to something less than one. Thus the domain is <m>x\leq -1</m> or <m>x\geq 1</m>. The outputs of <m>u = x^2-1</m> over this domain are all <m>u\geq 0</m>, thus the entire range of <m>\sqrt{u}</m> will be covered. Thus the range of <m>y = \sqrt{x^2-1}</m> is all <m>y\geq 0</m>.
			</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 4.18</term>. <em>Decompose <m>y = h(x) = \dfrac{2}{x^2-9}</m> as an inside function and outside function and use that decomposition to find the domain of <m>h</m> as in the previous example.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			<p>
				One important application of the idea of function composition is that of <em>inverse functions. In short, the inverse of a given function undoes the action of that function. This leads us to the following formal definition:</em>
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
			<p>
				<term>Definition of the Inverse Function</term> Given a function <m>y = f(x)</m>, the <em>inverse function to <m>f</m> is the function <m>x = f^{-1}(y)</m> such that <me>f^{-1}(f(x)) = x\ \mbox{and}\ f(f^{-1}(y)) = y.</me> The inputs of the inverse function are the outputs of <m>f</m>, the outputs of the inverse function are the inputs of <m>f</m>, and the two functions undo one another.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
			<p>
				<term>Example 4.19</term>.
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				Consider the function defined by the expression <me>y = f(x) = (x-4)^3 + 3.</me> By breaking this down into steps (decomposing the function), we are able to sequentially build the inverse function <me>x = f^{-1}(y) = \sqrt[3]{y-3} + 4.</me>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				In the Equation Practice worksheet, problem 3, we found the inverse of the function <me>y =g(x) = \sqrt[3]{4x-7}</me> to be <me>x = g^{-1}(y) = \frac{y^3+7}{4}.</me> We then used the inverse function to solve for <m>x</m> given several outputs. In this way, we may think of the inverse of a function as the general equation solving function, provided it’s just a number on the opposite side of the equation from the function.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p>

			<p>
				
			</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

			<p>
				The characterization of an inverse function as an equation solving function allows us to give an algebraic procedure for finding expressions of inverse functions even when we may not see how to reverse the process of the given function; simply write down the equation defining the function <m>y=f(x)</m>, and solve for <m>x</m> in terms of <m>y</m>.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 4.20</term>. <em>Find the inverse <m>f^{-1}(y)</m> for the function <me>y = f(x) = \frac{4-3x}{7-9x}.</me></em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			<p>
				The graph of the inverse to a given function has a particularly nice relationship to the graph of its parent function. To graph the inverse to a function <m>y=f(x)</m>, simply take the entire picture of the graph of <m>f</m>, including axis labels, and reflect it across the line through the origin making a 45 degree angle with the positive <m>x</m> axis.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 4.21</term>. <em>Why does it not make sense to graph <m>f</m> and <m>f^{-1}</m> on the same set of axes?</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

		</subsection>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="families-of-functions">
		<title>Families of Functions</title>

		<p>
			In this chapter we will cover the most important families of function of applied algebra. Because of their importance of these families in applications, each section will begin with a motivating real world example and end with a discussion of other applications. Throughout this chapter we will apply all the skills and concepts that appeared previously in this book.
		</p>

		<p>
			Before we begin, let’s clarify what we mean by a <em>family of functions. In the symbolic sense, a family of functions is a collection of functions that is defined by a specific algebraic form, often with some set of numbers that appear as parameters in the definition of the family. The function families we will study, and their associated algebraic forms, are the following:</em>
		</p>

		<p><ol>
			<li>
					<p>
			<term>Linear Functions</term> - These are functions of the form <m>y = f(x) = mx + b</m>, where <m>m</m> and <m>b</m> are constants (numbers).
		</p>
			</li>

			<li>
					<p>
			<term>Quadratic Functions</term> - These are functions of the form <m>y = q(x) = ax^2+bx+c</m>, where <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> are constants.
		</p>
			</li>

			<li>
					<p>
			<term>Exponential Functions</term> - These are functions of the form <m>y = p(x) = ab^{x}</m>, where <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are constants.
		</p>
			</li>

			<li>
					<p>
			<term>Power Functions</term> - These are functions of the form <m>y = q(x) = ax^{p}</m>, where <m>a</m> and <m>p</m> are constants.
		</p>
			</li>

		</ol></p>

		<p>
			For each family we will
		</p>

		<p><ol>
			<li>
					<p>
			discuss standard applications, thus leading to an embodied sense of how these functions behave,
		</p>
			</li>

			<li>
					<p>
			find formulas for these functions from a set of data,
		</p>
			</li>

			<li>
					<p>
			discuss various alternate algebraic forms they may take, with specific reasons to use different algebraic forms,
		</p>
			</li>

			<li>
					<p>
			discuss geometric properties of their graphs, and
		</p>
			</li>

			<li>
					<p>
			solve algebraic equations involving these functions.
		</p>
			</li>

		</ol></p>

		<p>
			One key thing to keep in mind is that all of the above tasks, and everything we have previously done in this course, are interconnected. Seeing the connections will help you think flexibly about these function families so that you can apply your knowledge assertively in subsequent math and science courses.
		</p>


		<subsection xml:id="linear-functions">
			<title>Linear Functions</title>

			<p>
				Linear function make up perhaps the most important class of functions in mathematics. Indeed, the basic premise of Calculus is to approximate more complicated functions with linear ones. However, despite their importance to higher mathematics, they come up in rather simple real world settings.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
			<p>
				<term>Example 5.1</term>. Fired Up Pizzeria charges <m>\$ 9.50</m> for a 12 inch pizza with no toppings, then an additional <m>\$ 1.50</m> per topping. Let’s consider the function <m>C</m> that takes as an input the number of toppings, <m>n</m>, and gives the cost of a pizza, <m>C(n)</m>, in dollars. To construct a formula for this function, we first give a table of values for its outputs for several inputs:<!-- linebreak -->
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
			<table>
				<caption></caption>
				<tabular>
				<row header="yes">
					<cell halign="center"><m>n</m> toppings</cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>0</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>1</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>2</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>3</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>4</m></cell>
					<cell halign="left"></cell>
				</row>
				<row class="odd">
					<cell halign="center"><m>C(n)</m> dollars</cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>9.50</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>11.00</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>12.50</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>14.00</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>15.50</m></cell>
					<cell halign="left"></cell>
				</row>
				</tabular>
			</table><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

			<p>
				The critical thing we notice in this table is that each time the input increases by one unit, an additional <m>\$ 1.50</m> is added to the cost. Hence, the number of times we add <m>1.50</m> to the initial (<m>n=0</m>) cost of <m>\$ 9.50</m> is equal to the input <m>n</m>. This process of repeated addition is precisely the definition of adding <m>1.5 n</m> to <m>9.5</m>, hence we have the formula <me>C(n) = 9.5 + 1.5 n.</me> Using the table and/or the formula, we may then graph <m>C</m> (fig. 5.1).
			</p>

			<p>
				In this picture we have plotted the graph between integer values of <m>n</m>, even though that may not make sense for this function, so that we can see the defining feature of the graph; it is a straight line. Due to the geometric properties of triangles, we see that the ratio of the change in the output divided by the change input is always equal to <m>1.5</m>. This value is called the <em>slope of this line.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->


			<subsubsection xml:id="intro-to-linear-functions">
				<title>Intro to Linear Functions</title>

				<p>
					Using the introductory example given above, we may characterize linear functions as in the following table:<!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
				<p>
					A <term>Linear Function is <m>\ldots</m></term>
				</p>

				<table>
					<caption></caption>
					<tabular>
					<row class="odd">
						<cell halign="left">Linear Function</cell>
						<cell halign="center"><m>\longrightarrow</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left">A process applied to the input that adds a fixed amount <m>m</m> to the output for each additional unit of input.</cell>
					</row>
					<row class="even">
						<cell halign="left"> </cell>
						<cell halign="center"><m>\longrightarrow</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left">A function of the form <m>y = f(x) = mx+b</m>, where <m>m</m> and <m>b</m> are constants.</cell>
					</row>
					<row class="odd">
						<cell halign="left"> </cell>
						<cell halign="center"><m>\longrightarrow</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left">A function whose graph is a non-vertical line.</cell>
					</row>
					</tabular>
				</table><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

				<p>
					Note that when we say that a function is of the form <m>f(x) = mx+b</m>, what we really mean is that it can be put into that form throught some algebraic manipulation. The graphical meaning of the parameters <m>m</m> and <m>b</m> are as follows:
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>Graphical Meaning of <m>m</m> and <m>b</m></term><!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					<m>m</m> is the slope of the line. That is, given  two points <m>(x_1,y_1)</m> and <m>(x_2,y_2)</m>, that lie on the graph of <m>f</m>, <m>m</m> is the ratio <me>m = \frac{y_1-y_2}{x_1-x_2}.</me>
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					If <m>m&gt;0</m>, then the graph increases from left to right.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					If <m>m&lt;0</m>, then the graph decreases from left to right.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					If <m>m=0</m>, then the graph is a horizontal line at height <m>b</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					If <m>|m|</m> is larger, the the line is steeper.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>b</m> is the output of <m>f</m> when <m>x=0</m>. In other words, it is the <m>y</m>-intercept of the graph of <m>f</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.2</term>. Because a line is uniquely determined by two points, it is possible to find the formula for a linear function whose graph contains a given pair of points (provided the two points do not lie on a vertical line). For instance, suppose we are given that <m>(1,3)</m> and <m>(3,4)</m> are on the graph of <m>f(x) = mx +b</m>, and we want to find <m>m</m> and <m>b</m>. First we compute the slope: <me>m = \frac{4-3}{3-1} = \frac{1}{2}.</me> Then we use the facts that <m>f</m> is of the form <m>f(x) = \frac{1}{2}x+b</m> and one of the two points is on the graph by substituting and solving for <m>b</m>: <me>\begin{aligned}
3 &amp; = &amp; \frac{1}{2}\cdot 1 + b\\
 &amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
b &amp; = &amp; \frac{5}{2}.\end{aligned}</me> Thus <m>f(x) = \frac{1}{2}x + \frac{5}{2}</m>. Another way to see how this process works is by noting that <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> is added to the output for every extra unit of input. By starting at <m>(1,3)</m> and subtracting <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> once to get back to when <m>x=0</m>, we also get <m>b=f(0)=\frac{5}{2}</m>.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.3</term>. <em>In the last example, we noted that finding the formula for a linear function would not work if the line was vertical. Explain the following:</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em>You cannot determine the slope of a vertical line from two points on that line.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>The equation of a vertical line has the form <m>x=a</m>, where <m>a</m> is a number.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					In practical applications, one can often recognize linear functions by noting a rate of change parameter.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.4</term>. Suppose we wish to find the profit <m>P</m> of selling <m>q</m> widgets. This is the revenue we get from selling the widgets minus the cost of producing them. We sell the widgets for <m>\$ 35</m> a piece, and it costs <m>\$ 1000</m> to set up production, plus <m>\$ 15</m> to make each widget. The units of <m>\$ /\mbox{widget}</m> on the selling price and production cost are both rates of change of the form <m>(\mbox{function output})/(\mbox{function input})</m>. This indicates the function is likely a linear function. Going to the formula we get <me>P = (\mbox{revenue}) - (\mbox{cost}) = 35q - (1000 + 15q).</me> This simplifies to the linear function <me>P = 20q - 1000.</me> Here we see that <m>\$ 1000</m> will be spent no matter how many widgets are sold, and we get a net profit of <m>\$ 20</m> for each widget sold.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.5</term>. <em>A ski shop rents skis for a fixed initial payment of <m>A</m> dollars and a charge of <m>r</m> dollars per day they are used. If a skier pays a total of <m>A + 6r</m> dollars, what is the meaning of the number <m>6</m>? Explain your answer as completely as possible.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="forms-of-linear-functions">
				<title>Forms of Linear Functions</title>

				<p>
					The form <m>y = f(x) = mx + b</m> of a linear function is known as <em>slope-intercept form. It is a very useful form. A more general (but non-unique) form is known as </em>point-slope form.<!-- linebreak -->**
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>Point-Slope Form of a Linear Function</term><!-- linebreak -->The linear function of slope <m>m</m> passing through the point <m>(x_0,y_0)</m> has the form <me>y = f(x) = y_0 + m(x-x_0).</me>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

				<p>
					In order to understand point-slope form, all you need to do is ask (and answer) the following two questions:
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					Is <m>f(x) = y_0 + m(x-x_0)</m> the formula for a linear function with slope <m>m</m>? The answer is yes. All one needs to do is simplify and collect like terms to see that <m>f(x) = mx + (y_0 - mx_0)</m>. Thus we can say <m>b = y_0 - mx_0</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Does the graph of <m>f(x) = y_0 + m(x-x_0)</m> pass through the point <m>(x_0,y_0)</m>? Again the answer is yes because <m>f(x_0) = y_0 + m(x_0-x_0) = y_0</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					The graphical difference between point-slope form and slope-intercept form is that slope-intercept form puts on display the <m>y</m>-intercept, whereas slope-intercept form displays another point on the graph. Equipped with point-slope form, it is somewhat easier to find a formula for a linear function given two points; all you need to do is compute the slope.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.6</term>. <em>Use point-slope form to find a formula for the linear function whose graph passes through <m>(12,7)</m> and <m>(15,89)</m>. Once you have the formula in point slope form, find the <m>y</m>-intercept and write it in slope-intercept form.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.7</term>. <em>The slope-intercept form of the formula for a linear function is actually equal to the point-slope form for a specific point on the graph. What point is that?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					Since the graphs of linear functions are lines, it makes sense to ask whether the two lines are parallel or perpendicular. To see whether two lines are parallel, they simply must have the same slope. So see whether two lines are perpendicular, consider the following figure:
				</p>

				<p>
					From this (with triangles added to illustrate slope), we see that the magnitude of the change in <m>y</m> for an associated change in <m>x</m> on one graph is the same as the magnitude of the change in <m>x</m> for an associated change in <m>y</m> on the perpendicular graph. Also, the sign of the slope is opposite. Hence the slope of a line perpendicular to a line of slope <m>m</m> is <m>-\dfrac{1}{m}</m>.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.8</term>. <em>How can you tell the lines <m>y = 3x+1</m> and <m>y=3x+17</m> never intersect, without doing any algebra?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.9</term>. <em>Do the graphs of <m>f(x) = 3x+1</m> and <m>g(x) = 25 + 3(x-8)</m> intersect? Why or why not?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="applications-of-linear-functions">
				<title>Applications of Linear Functions</title>

				<p>
					Linear functions arise in real-world applications involving one variable that changes at a constant rate relative to another. Once the linear function is found, the problems usually boil down to
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					finding an output for a given input (evaluating),
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					finding the input for a given output (solving a simple equations), or
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					finding when two linear functions are equal (find when graphs intersect).
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					Each of these problems is actually relatively straightforward from an algebraic point of view, given that you have formulas for your functions. The main difficulty is turning the words of the real world into mathematics.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.10</term>. As one climbs a mountain, the air temperature decreases by about <m>3^{\circ}</m>F for every <m>1000</m> foot increase in elevation. Suppose the temperature is <m>60^{\circ}</m>F when at an elevation of <m>2000</m> feet above sea level. Suppose we want the answer to the following questions:
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					What will the temperature be at an elevation of <m>14,439</m> feet?
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					What should the elevation be to be a <q>crisp</q> room temperature of <m>65^{\circ}</m>F?
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p>

				<p>
					: Our first task must be to find a formula for temperature as a function of elevation. To achieve this, we first have to name variables (this can be hard at first). Let <m>T</m> be the temperature, in <m>^{\circ}</m>F, at an elevation <m>h</m> feet above sea level. The problem describes a rate of change of <m>-3/1000</m> in <m>^{\circ}</m>F/ft; this will be the slope of our linear function. This slope can often be seen using the units as the units of slope must be output units divided by input units. The sign is negative because the temperature decreases at this rate as <m>h</m> increases. The problem then describes a point on the graph of this function, <m>(2000,60)</m>. Using point-slope form, we have <me>T = -\frac{3}{1000}(h-2000) + 60.</me> The answer to part (a) is then obtained by substituting <m>14,493</m> for <m>h</m> to get <me>T = -\frac{3}{1000}(14493-2000) + 60\approx 22.521^{\circ}\mbox{F}.</me> To answer part (b), we need to substitute <m>65</m> for <m>T</m>, and solve for <m>h</m>: <me>\begin{aligned}
65 &amp; = &amp; -\frac{3}{1000}(h-2000) + 60\\
 &amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
h &amp; = &amp; \frac{1000}{3}\approx 333.33\ \mbox{ft}.\end{aligned}</me>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.11</term>. <em>Why is the formula for <m>T</m> as a function of <m>h</m> given in the last example more useful to a climber whose elevation is near 2000 feet than to one near sea level? What equivalent formula would be more useful to someone near sea level? Explain.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.12</term>. <em>The ideal gas law says that <me>PV = nR(T-z),</me> where <m>P</m> is the pressure of a gas, <m>V</m> is its volume, <m>T</m> is its temperature in <m>^{\circ}</m>C, <m>n</m> is the number of moles of gas, <m>R</m> is a constant, and <m>z</m> is the value of absolute zero in <m>^{\circ}</m>C. If <m>n</m> and <m>V</m> are constant, like when the gas is in a sealed container, we have a linear function for <m>P</m> as a function of <m>T</m>: <me>P = \frac{nR}{V} (T-z).</me></em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em>What is the slope of the graph of <m>P</m> (just in symbols, not the number)?</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Suppose we measure <m>P</m> to be <m>3.5</m> when <m>T = 70</m>, and <m>3.602</m> when <m>T = 80</m>. Find the slope of the graph of <m>P</m> from this data.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Use the data and the value of the slope from part (b) to give an approximate value of <m>z</m>. Is this close to the value you may have learned in a science class (or can look up)?</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>
		</subsection>

		<subsection xml:id="quadratic-functions">
			<title>Quadratic Functions</title>

			<p>
				Quadratic functions are probably the simplest non-linear functions to study. The adjective <em>quadratic comes from the Latin word for square, </em>quadr<m>\overline{a}</m>tus. This is because the addition of a term involving <m>x^2</m> comes from measuring areas. Thinking of quadratic functions as ones that measure rectangular areas is what allows us to see that quadratic functions can be used to model positions of objects whose acceleration is constant.**
			</p>


			<subsubsection xml:id="intro-to-quadratic-functions">
				<title>Intro to Quadratic Functions</title>

				<p>
					A <em>quadratic function is one of the form <m>y = f(x) = ax^2+bx+c</m>, where <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> are constants with <m>a\neq 0</m>.</em>
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.13</term>. Let us consider the simplest possible quadratic function <m>f(x) = x^2</m>. By plotting points, we may construct its graph:
				</p>

				<p>
					There are several observations we can make about the graph, along with connections to the algebraic expression defining this function.
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					Our first observation is that the outputs of <m>f(x) = x^2</m> are never negative. This is simply due to the fact that the square of any real number is either zero (only when <m>x=0</m>) or positive. Not all quadratic functions have non-negative graphs, but the fact that <m>x^2</m> is never negative will be very useful in analyzing other quadratic functions.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Another observation is that the graph is symmetric about the <m>y</m>-axis. This is because for any real number <m>a</m>, <m>(-a)^2 = a^2</m>. Thus the output is the same at <m>x=a</m> as it is for <m>x=-a</m>. We will see that the graph of every quadratic function has some vertical axis of symmetry.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					We see that the graph is *concave-up. That is, as you move from left to right, the slope between points on the graph is increasing. More precisely, using the input-output table<!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
					
					</li>

				</ul></p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
				<table>
					<caption></caption>
					<tabular>
					<row header="yes">
						<cell halign="center"><m>x</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>-3</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>-2</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>-1</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>0</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>1</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>2</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>3</m></cell>
					</row>
					<row class="odd">
						<cell halign="center"><m>f(x)</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>9</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>4</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>1</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>0</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>1</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>4</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>9</m></cell>
					</row>
					</tabular>
				</table><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

				<p>
					we may construct an table of slopes:
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
				<table>
					<caption></caption>
					<tabular>
					<row header="yes">
						<cell halign="left">Points on the Graph</cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>(-3,9)</m> and <m>(-2,4)</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>(-2,4)</m> and <m>(-1,1)</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>(-1,1)</m> and <m>(0,0)</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>(0,0)</m> and <m>(1,1)</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>(1,1)</m> and <m>(2,4)</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>(2,4)</m> and <m>(3,9)</m></cell>
					</row>
					<row class="odd">
						<cell halign="left">Slope of Connecting Line</cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>-5</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>-3</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>-1</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>1</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>3</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left"><m>5</m></cell>
					</row>
					</tabular>
				</table><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

				<p>
					We see that the slope is increasing. Observing that the slope actually increases by a constant amount for constant steps from left to right is the key to applications of quadratic functions. If the slope were decreasing as we moved from left to right, we would say the graph is <em>concave down.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					These are the observations we made about <m>f(x) = x^2</m>, which has parameters <m>a=1</m>, <m>b=0</m>, and <m>c=0</m>. Throughout this section we will see how the parameters <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> affect the placement of the maximum or minimum output, the axis of symmetry, and the concavity of the graph of a quadratic function, as well as their practical implications.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.14</term>. <em>In the definition of a quadratic function, it was noted that the parameter <m>a</m> could not be zero. Why would we insist that <m>a</m> be nonzero to define a quadratic function? What do we call a function of the form <m>f(x) = ax^2+bx+c</m> when <m>a=0</m>?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					Just as the parameters <m>m</m> and <m>b</m> have graphical interpretations for the family of linear functions, the parameters <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> have graphical interpretations for quadratic functions. However, because the family of quadratic functions involves three parameters instead of two, they are more complicated.
				</p>

				<p>
					First let’s deal with the parameter <m>c</m>. This one is simple; it’s just the output of <m>f(x) = ax^2+bx+c</m> when <m>x=0</m>. Thus the <m>y</m>-intercept of <m>f(x) = ax^2+bx+c</m> is at <m>(0,c)</m>. The second easiest parameter to understand is <m>a</m>. The sign of <m>a</m> tells use whether the parabola (the graph of a quadratic function is called a <em>parabola) is concave up or concave down. To see this, notice that if <m>a</m> is positive, then for very large values of <m>x</m>, <m>ax^2</m> is positive and larger in absolute value than both <m>bx</m> and <m>c</m>. This means that the parabola must be opening up. Likewise, if <m>a</m> is negative, then the parabola is concave down. The parameter <m>b</m> is more complicated, and we will leave its exact meaning for the next section.</em>
				</p>

				<p>
					One of the primary skills associated to any family of functions is solving equations of the form <me>f(x) = \mbox{a number}.</me> When <m>f</m> is a quadratic function, we have already discussed one of the most important solution methods: factoring. To solve an equation of the form <me>ax^2+bx+c = d,</me> one must just subtract <m>d</m> from both sides, factor, and use the zero factors principle to solve. The <m>x</m>-intercepts, or zeros, of a quadratic function can be seen when we write it in <em>factored form: <me>f(x) = ax^2 + bx+c = a(x-r)(x-s).</me> In this form <m>a</m> is the same as it is in the expanded form, while <m>r</m> and <m>s</m> are the zeros. Notice that not all quadratic functions can be put into factored form as they may not have any real zeros.</em>
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.15</term>. <em>When <m>f(x) = ax^2 + bx + c = a(x-r)(x-s)</m>, we can use the factors <m>(x-r)</m> and <m>(x-s)</m> to really see what the graph of <m>f</m> looks like, and how <m>a</m> influences it. In what follows, suppose <m>r</m> and <m>s</m> are generic real numbers with <m>r&lt;s</m>.</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em>On a single set of axes graph the lines <m>y = x-r</m> and <m>y = x-s</m>. Use this graph to find the values of <m>x</m> where <m>x-r</m> and <m>x-s</m> have the same sign and where they have different signs. Use this do decide when <m>y=(x-r)(x-s)</m> is positive and when it is negative.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Use your answers from part (a) to sketch a graph of <m>y = (x-r)(x-s)</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Using your graph from part (b) and reasoning from part (a), explain why the sign of the parameter <m>a</m> tells you whether the graph of <m>f(x) = a(x-r)(x-s)</m> opens up or down.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="forms-of-quadratic-functions">
				<title>Forms of Quadratic Functions</title>

				<p>
					There are three very useful forms of a quadratic function <m>f(x) = ax^2+bx+c</m>. The first two are familiar at this point:
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					Standard Form: <m>f(x) = ax^2+bx+c</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Factored Form: <m>f(x) = a(x-r)(x-s)</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					The third form is new, and is the quadratic analogue of the point-slope form of a linear function.<!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>Vertex Form of a Quadratic Function</term><!-- linebreak -->Every quadratic function may be put in the form <me>y = f(x) = a(x-h)^2+k.</me> The axis of symmetry of the graph is <m>x=h</m>, and the maximum (if <m>a&lt;0</m>) or minimum (if <m>a&gt;0</m>) output of <m>f</m> is <m>f(h) = k</m>.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

				<p>
					The usefulness of vertex form is well illustrated in the following example:
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.16</term>. Let <m>f(x) = -2(x-3)^2 + 5</m>. We wish to
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					Find the zeros of <m>f</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Find the maximum or minimum possible output of <m>f</m>. This will tell you the range of <m>f</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Sketch the graph of <m>f</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p>

				<p>
					
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					Based on prior experience, one may be tempted to expand to standard form and factor. Doing this we obtain the equation <me>-2x^2+12x-13 = 0.</me> However, when we try to factor, we see there aren’t any ways to do it using only integers. On further reflection, we can see that the vertex form makes it easier to solve, because it breaks a quadratic function into a straightforward process applied to the variable <m>x</m>. From the vertex form we can say this function does the following:
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					subtract <m>3</m> from <m>x</m>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					square <term>S1</term>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					multiply <term>S2</term> by <m>-2</m>, and finally
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					adds <m>5</m> to <term>S3</term>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					The reverse process applied to any output of <m>f</m> will be
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					subtract <m>5</m>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					and divide by <m>-2</m>, then
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					take the positive or negative square root, and finally
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					add <m>3</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					Applying this to zero, we get the zeros <me>x = 3\pm \sqrt{\frac{5}{2}}.</me> We can apply this to any proposed output, as long as the thing we need to take the square root of is not negative. <term>Note:</term> This reverse process does not actually describe an inverse function; the step where the reverse process allows for multiple possibilities prevents this process from defining a function, which must only yield one input for each output.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					A slight rearrangement of the vertex form to look like <m>f(x) = 5-2(x-3)^2</m> makes it clear that the range is all <m>y\leq 5</m>. Because <m>(x-3)^2</m> is never negative, some quantity is always being subtracted from <m>5</m>. The maximum possible output is also clearly <m>5</m>, and it occurs when <m>x=3</m>. We can also see this from an algebraic expression for the reverse process applied to <m>y</m>: <me>x = 3\pm\sqrt{\frac{y-5}{-2}}.</me> The possible values of <m>y</m> in this expression are those that make <m>\frac{y-5}{-2}</m> non-negative. Thus we must have <m>y\leq 5</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Plotting the vertex, the <m>y</m>-intercept, and a few points to the left and right of the vertex gives us a good graph:
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p>

				<p>
					
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.17</term>. <em>In the last example, we found the zeros of <m>f(x) = -2(x-3)^2+5</m> to be <m>x=3\pm \sqrt{\frac{5}{2}}</m>. The zeros are also supposed to appear in the factored form as <m>r</m> and <m>s</m>. Expand the right-hand side of the equation and collect like terms to verify that <me>-2x^2+12x-13 = -2\left(x-\left(3-\sqrt{\frac{5}{2}}\right)\right)\left(x-\left(3+\sqrt{\frac{5}{2}}\right)\right).</me></em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					One must now ask how we find the vertex form of a given quadratic function, also known as <em>completing the square. There are a number of ways to do this. The way we present is very flexible, and may be modified to find useful formulas for many other types of functions. To find the vertex form, simply write down the proposed form with <m>h</m> and <m>k</m>, then expand and collect like terms to get a system of equations that you may solve for <m>h</m> and <m>k</m>. The following example illustrates this procedure nicely.</em>
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.18</term>. Find the vertex form of <m>f(x) = 5x^2-15x+11</m> and use it to find the zeros of <m>f</m>.<!-- linebreak --> We see <m>a=5</m>, thus we must have <me>\begin{aligned}
5x^2-15x+11 &amp; = &amp; 5(x-h)^2+k\\
\ &amp; = &amp; 5(x^2-2hx+h^2) + k\\
\ &amp; = &amp; 5x^2 - 10hx + 5h^2 + k.\end{aligned}</me> Now we match like terms on either side of the equation to obtain the system of equations <me>\begin{aligned}
-10h &amp; = &amp; -15\ \mbox{(from the $x$ terms)}\\
5h^2 + k&amp; = &amp; 11\ \mbox{(from the constant terms)}\end{aligned}</me> Solving this system we have <m>h = \frac{3}{2}</m> and <m>k = -\frac{1}{4}</m>. As in the last example, we can solve <me>5\left(x-\frac{3}{2}\right)^2 - \frac{1}{4} = 0</me> in a straightforward way to get <m>x = \frac{3}{2}\pm\frac{1}{\sqrt{20}} = \frac{3}{2}\pm\frac{1}{2\sqrt{5}}</m>.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

				<p>
					One may find the vertex form of a quadratic in full generality in terms of the parameters <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> (<term>Do not attempt to memorize this!</term>): <me>ax^2+bx+c = a\left(x-\left(\frac{-b}{2a}\right)\right)^2 + \frac{4ac-b^2}{4a^2}.</me> It is easier to just set up and solve the system of equations, which you’ll get faster at with practice, than to commit this to memory. The only reason to write down the general formula for vertex form is to derive the <em>quadratic formula for the zeros of a quadratic: <me>x = \frac{-b\pm\sqrt{b^2-4ac}}{2a}.</me> Observe that <m>-\frac{b}{2a}</m> is where the vertex is, which is halfway between the zeros. This may be seen as the graphical meaning of the parameter <m>b</m>.</em>
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.19</term>. <em>Use the quadratic formula to find the zeros of the function in the above example, <m>f(x) = 5x^2-15x+11</m>. Simplify your answer to show that it is equivalent to the answer given in the example.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.20</term>. <em>Find the vertex form of the following quadratic functions. Use it to find the maximum or minimum output as well as the zeros of each function, if the zeros exist. Simplify your answers as much as possible, but do not use a calculator.</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>f(x) = 2x^2-4x+1</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>g(x) = 2x^2-4x+5</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>h(x) = 13x^2 -8x + 1</m></em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					The following is a summary of the forms of a quadratic function and what their parameters mean.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>Forms of a Quadratic Function, <m>f</m>, and What the Parameters Mean</term><!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					Standard form: <m>f(x) = ax^2+bx+c</m>
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					The <m>y</m>-intercept of the graph of <m>f</m> is at <m>(0,c)</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					If <m>a&gt;0</m>, the graph is an upward opening parabola.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					If <m>a&lt;0</m>, the graph is a downward opening parabola.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Factored form: <m>f(x) = a(x-r)(x-s)</m>.
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
					The <m>x</m>-intercepts (if they exist) of the graph of <m>f</m> are at <m>(r,0)</m> and <m>(s,0)</m>.
					</li>

				</ul></p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Vertex Form: <m>f(x) = a(x-h)^2 + k</m>
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					The vertex of the graph of <m>f</m> is at <m>(h,k)</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					This form is extremely useful for solving equations when factoring proves difficult.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>
					</li>

				</ul></p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.21</term>. Find a formula for the quadratic function whose graph is shown below:
				</p>

				<p>
					 We see that the vertex is at <m>(3,3)</m>, hence the quadratic function may be written in the form <me>f(x) = a(x-3)^2 + 3.</me> Using the fact that <m>(1,1)</m> is also on the graph, we have the equation <me>a(1-3)^2 + 3 = 1.</me> Solving, we get <m>a= -\frac{1}{2}</m>, thus <m>f(x) = -\frac{1}{2}(x-3)^2 + 3</m>.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.22</term>. <em>Find a formula for a quadratic function whose graph has <m>x</m>-intercepts at <m>(1,0)</m> and <m>(5,0)</m>, and <m>y</m>-intercept at <m>(0,7)</m>.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="applications-of-quadratic-functions">
				<title>Applications of Quadratic Functions</title>

				<p>
					The first application we can see for quadratic functions comes from their original purpose, finding areas. Now that we know how to find the vertex form of a quadratic function, we can find the maximum or minimum possible values of functions that describe area.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.23</term>. Suppose a farmer wants to fence off a rectangular area with three sides of a rectangle, using a river as the fourth side. She has 100 yards of fence to use and wishes to enclose as large an area as possible. Let <m>x</m> denote the length of the side of the rectangle parallel to the river and <m>w</m> be the length of the side perpendicular to the rive, both measured in yards. Since she has <m>100</m> yards of fence to use, we have the relation <me>x+2w = 100.</me> The area is given by <m>A = xw</m>. To obtain the area as a function of <m>x</m>, we substitute <m>w=\frac{100-x}{2}</m> (from the constraint) for <m>w</m> to get <me>A(x) = x\left(\frac{100-x}{2}\right) = -\frac{x^2}{2}+50x.</me> When we find the vertex form of this function we find <m>h=50</m> and <m>-\frac{h^2}{2} + k = 0</m>, hence <m>k = 1250</m>. Thus <me>A(x) = -\frac{1}{2}(x-50)^2 + 1250.</me> This means the maximum area is <m>1,250</m> yd<m>{^2}</m>, which occurs when <m>x=50</m> and <m>w = 25</m>. 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.24</term>. <em>How much fence would the farmer in the last problem need if she wanted the maximum possible enclosed area to be <m>2000</m> yd<m>^2</m>?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					One of the most important applications of quadratic functions comes as a prelude to really doing differential Calculus. The application is modeling the motion of objects with constant acceleration. It was Galileo Galilei who reasoned that all massive objects objects accelerate at the same constant rate when dropped, no matter what the mass is (neglecting air resistance). What we would like to do is construct a function that gives the height of a dropped object <m>t</m> seconds after it was dropped. What type of function should we use? We know that linear functions have a constant rate of change, thus if a linear function is used to describe the position of a moving object, that object’s velocity must be constant. This would mean its acceleration must be zero. To model an object whose acceleration is a nonzero constant, we must construct a function whose rate of change changes at a constant rate.
				</p>

				<p>
					Let’s consider a candidate quadratic function <m>f(t) = at^2+bt+c</m>. In order to find the rate of change of the rate of change (let’s call this quantity acceleration), we must first find its rate of change for a small change, <m>\Delta t</m>, in <m>t</m>. To figure this out, let’s think flexibly about the terms of <m>f(t)</m> as areas being summed up. The constant term, <m>c</m>, can represent a <m>1\times c</m> rectangle, which does not change at all for a <m>\Delta t</m> change in <m>t</m>. The term <m>bt</m> can represent a <m>b\times t</m> rectangle. If the side of length <m>t</m> increases by <m>\Delta t</m>, the area increases by <m>b\Delta t</m> as in the following figure:<!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

				<p>
					The shaded area is the total change in <m>bt</m>. Dividing this by <m>\Delta t</m> to make it a rate of change, we find that the rate of change in <m>bt</m> is <m>b</m> (this should not be surprising, <m>bt</m> is linear with slope <m>b</m>). Now we will consider the term <m>at^2</m> as the area of a <m>at\times t</m> rectangle. If <m>t</m> changes by <m>\Delta t</m>, the total change in <m>at^2</m> is represented by the shaded area in the following figure:
				</p>

				<p>
					Thus the total change in <m>at^2</m> for a change in <m>t</m> of <m>\Delta t</m> is given by <m>2at\Delta t + a(\Delta t)^2</m>. Dividing by <m>\Delta t</m> to obtain a rate of change, we get <m>2at + a\Delta t</m>. Hence the total rate of change in <m>f(t) = at^2+bt + c</m>, at a given <m>t</m> value changing by <m>\Delta t</m>, is <me>\mbox{total rate of change} = 2at + a\Delta t + b.</me> Considering <m>\Delta t</m> to be <q>infinitesimally small</q>, we find the instantaneous rate of change (velocity) is <m>2at + b</m>. This is a linear function with slope <m>2a</m>! That means that its rate of change (acceleration) is constant and equal to <m>2b</m>. This means we have a new characterization of quadratic functions to go along with their algebraic form:
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
				<p>
					A <term>Quadratic Function is <m>\ldots</m></term>
				</p>

				<table>
					<caption></caption>
					<tabular>
					<row class="odd">
						<cell halign="left">Linear Function</cell>
						<cell halign="center"><m>\longrightarrow</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left">A function of the form <m>y = f(x) = ax^2+bx+c</m>, where <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> are constants.</cell>
					</row>
					<row class="even">
						<cell halign="left"> </cell>
						<cell halign="center"><m>\longrightarrow</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left">A function whose graph is a parabola.</cell>
					</row>
					<row class="odd">
						<cell halign="left"> </cell>
						<cell halign="center"><m>\longrightarrow</m></cell>
						<cell halign="left">A function whose second rate of change (acceleration) is constant.</cell>
					</row>
					</tabular>
				</table><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

				<p>
					<term>Remark:</term> The idea of computing instantaneous rates of change is central to Calculus. Re-read this section carefully now, then do it again when you learn about derivatives.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.44</term>. Now back to Galileo’s problem. He measured the acceleration of an object to be downward at <m>9.8</m> m/s<m>^2</m>. Thus, to model the height of a projectile, we should use a quadratic function with leading term <m>-4.9t^2</m>. The initial velocity, <m>v_0</m>, should be the constant term of the velocity function (<m>2at+b</m> above), so the linear term should be <m>v_0 t</m>. The initial height is just the vertical intercept. Hence we have the formula for the height of a object, in meters after <m>t</m> seconds, with initial height <m>h_0</m> and initial velocity <m>v_0</m>: <me>h(t) = -4.9t^2 + v_0t + h_0.</me>
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					To find when it hits the ground, find the larger of its zeros.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					To find the maximal height, find the vertex.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.25</term>. <em>What is the instantaneous rate of change in <m>f(t) = t^3</m>? Explain why your answer is correct using the volume of a cube as in Question 2.6.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>
		</subsection>

		<subsection xml:id="exponential-functions">
			<title>Exponential Functions</title>

			<p>
				Exponential functions are common in applications where the rate of change is not described in absolute terms, but in relative terms as a percent rate of change. For instance, suppose we say a population, <m>P</m>, is growing at a rate of <m>50\%</m> per year with an initial value of <m>1000</m>. This means that to find the population next year, we find the population of the current year, multiply it by <m>0.5</m>, and add it to the current population. Then we can construct a table of values, with the input <m>t</m> being measured in years:<!-- linebreak -->
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
			<table>
				<caption></caption>
				<tabular>
				<row header="yes">
					<cell halign="right"><m>t</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>0</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>1</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>2</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>3</m></cell>
				</row>
				<row class="odd">
					<cell halign="right"><m>P</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>1000</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>1500</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>2250</m></cell>
					<cell halign="right"><m>3375</m></cell>
				</row>
				</tabular>
			</table><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

			<p>
				We can notice that the slope, which is the absolute rate of change, is not constant. Between the points <m>(0,1000)</m> and <m>(1,1500)</m>, the slope is <m>500</m>. The slope between the points <m>(1,1500)</m> and <m>(2,2250)</m> is <m>750</m>. However, if we take the ratio of consecutive outputs, we get a constant: <me>\frac{1500}{1000} = \frac{2250}{1500} = \frac{3375}{2250}  = 1.5.</me> What this shows is that each time the input increases by <m>1</m>, the output gets multiplied by <m>1.5</m> one more time. Since repeated multiplication is denoted by an exponent, we see that <me>P = 1000(1.5)^t.</me> Functions with this basic form are known as exponential functions.
			</p>


			<subsubsection xml:id="intro-to-exponential-functions">
				<title>Intro to Exponential Functions</title>

				<p>
					An <em>exponential function is a function of the form <m>f(x) = ab^x</m>, where <m>a\neq 0</m> and <m>b&gt;0</m>.</em>
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.26</term>. Consider <m>f(x) = 2(1.5)^x</m>. We can plot some points to construct a graph of this function.
				</p>

				<p>
					We can make several observations about this graph and connect them to the algebraic form of this function.
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					First, notice that the <m>y</m>-intercept is at <m>(0,2)</m>. This is due to the fact that <m>f(0) = 2(1.5)^0</m>. Since any nonzero number raised to the zero power is <m>1</m>, we are just multiplying <m>2</m> by <m>1</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					We also can notice this function is increasing as you move from left to right. In fact, you can see that each point we plotted is exactly one and a half times higher above the <m>x</m>-axis than the point that was plotted one unit to its left. This is because the height is multiplied by <m>1.5</m> each time the input increases by one unit.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					If we move from right to left through negative values of <m>t</m>, all the outputs are less than <m>2</m> and getting smaller. This isn’t a truly different observation than the last one, but it’s a different perspective. This comes from the fact that when <m>t</m> is negative, we’re really dividing by positive powers of <m>1.5</m>. (Review you exponent rules now if you need to.)
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Finally, we notice that the outputs stay above the <m>x</m>-axis. This is because <m>(1.5)^t</m> is always positive, as it represents repeated multiplication of a positive number. If the <m>2</m> in front were replaced by a negative number, then the output would never be positive. Exponential functions never change signs.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.27</term>. <em>In the definition of an exponential function, we said that <m>a</m> cannot be zero and <m>b</m> had to be positive. Let’s think about why we would make such restrictions.</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em>If <m>a=0</m>, what simpler family of functions does <m>f(x) = ab^x</m> belong to?</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>If <m>b</m> is negative, what is a value of <m>x</m> that would make <m>b^{x}</m> undefined? (The answer is not zero.)</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>The Meaning of <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> in Exponential Functions</term><!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					<m>b</m> is the growth factor. Each time the input increases by one unit, the output is multiplied by another factor of <m>b</m>.
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					If <m>b&gt;1</m>, then the graph diverges away from the <m>x</m>-axis from left to right and gets arbitrarily close to the <m>x</m>-axis as <m>x\to-\infty</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					If <m>b&lt;1</m>, then the graph gets arbitrarily close to the <m>x</m>-axis as <m>x\to\infty</m>, and diverges away from the <m>x</m>-axis moving right to left.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>a</m> is the output of <m>f</m> when <m>x=0</m>. In other words, it is the <m>y</m>-intercept of the graph of <m>f</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.28</term>. <em>The domain of an exponential function is the set of all real numbers. What is the range? Your answer will depend of the value of <m>a</m>.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					As with all function families, when we say that a function has a specific form, we really mean that its defining formula is equivalent to that form. Often it is the case that a function is not presented in a specific form, but algebraic manipulation shows it to be in the specified family.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.29</term>. Let <m>f(x) = \dfrac{3(2)^{x+3}}{5^{x-1}}</m>. This function is not in the form <m>f(x) = ab^x</m>, but we may use some exponent rules to put it in that form: <me>f(x) = \frac{3(2)^{x+3}}{5^{x-1}} = \frac{3\cdot 2^3\cdot 2^{x}}{5^{-1}\cdot 5^{x}} = 120\left(\frac{2}{5}\right)^{x}.</me> Hence we see <m>a = 120</m> and <m>b=\frac{2}{5}</m>. Alternatively, we could use a table of outputs to decide this function is exponential and find its parameters:<!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
				<table>
					<caption></caption>
					<tabular>
					<row header="yes">
						<cell halign="right"><m>x</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>0</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>1</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>2</m></cell>
					</row>
					<row class="odd">
						<cell halign="right"><m>f(x)</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>120</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>48</m></cell>
						<cell halign="right"><m>19.2</m></cell>
					</row>
					</tabular>
				</table><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

				<p>
					The ratios of consecutive values are equal to <m>b</m>: <m>\frac{48}{120} = \frac{19.2}{48} =\frac{2}{5}</m>. The value at <m>t=0</m> is <m>a</m>. 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

				<p>
					Generally, if you know one of the parameters of an exponential function and a point on its graph, you can solve for the other parameter. In the next section we will go into detail of how to find formulas for exponential functions from two points on the graph, similar to how we did it for linear functions. We will also see possible reasons for alternatives to the standard <m>ab^x</m> form.
				</p>

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="forms-of-exponential-functions">
				<title>Forms of Exponential Functions</title>

				<p>
					Often we would like to find a formula for an exponential function when the initial condition and growth rate are not known. However, we often do know some information that is somehow equivalent to two points on the graph. To understand some of the useful forms of exponential functions, let’s first figure out how to find a formula given two points on the graph.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.30</term>. Suppose the points <m>(2,1)</m> and <m>(9,4)</m> are on the graph of <m>y=f(x) = ab^{x}</m>. We would like to determine <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>. To do this, we merely need to set up a system of equations and solve it. Using the input-output pairs, we have <me>\begin{aligned}
1 &amp; = &amp; ab^{2}\\
4 &amp; = &amp; ab^{9}.\end{aligned}</me> Using the first equation, we find <m>a = \frac{1}{b^2}</m>, which we can substitute into the second to get <me>\begin{aligned}
4 &amp; = &amp; \frac{1}{b^2}\cdot b^{9}\\
 &amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
b^{7} &amp; = &amp; 4 \\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
b &amp; = &amp; \sqrt[7]{4}.\end{aligned}</me> Then we find <m>a = \frac{1}{(\sqrt[7]{4})^{2}}</m>. Thus we have <m>f(x) = \frac{1}{(\sqrt[7]{4})^{2}} (\sqrt[7]{4})^x</m>. 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

				<p>
					This process for finding the equation of an exponential function is straightforward, but the final answer does not show the points the graph passes through in a transparent way. Instead, we may write it in the form <me>f(x)  = \frac{1}{(\sqrt[7]{4})^{2}} (\sqrt[7]{4})^x = 1\cdot 4^{\frac{x-2}{7}}.</me> In this form we can see that <m>f(2) = 1</m> and <m>f(9) = 4</m> quite easily.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.31</term>. <em>Show the manipulations, using exponent rules, that one must use to put the function from the example into the form shown above.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.32</term>. <em>Let <m>f(x) = 3\left(\frac{14}{3}\right)^{\frac{x-12}{5}}</m>. Find two points with integer coordinates that are obviously on the graph of <m>f</m>. Explain why they are obvious.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					Using the last two questions as motivation, we can introduce the following form of an exponential function:
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>Point-Factor-(Time Interval) Form for an Exponential Function</term><!-- linebreak -->An exponential function <m>f</m> that has the property that <m>f(x_0) = S</m> and grows by a factor of <m>M</m> over each time interval <m>T</m> has the form <me>f(x) = S(M)^{\frac{x-x_0}{T}}.</me> The initial value of this function is <m>\left(S(M)^{-\frac{x_0}{T}}\right)</m> and its growth factor per unit increase in input is <m>M^{\frac{1}{T}}</m>.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

				<p>
					This particular form of an exponential function may be thought of as analogous to the point-slope form of a linear function. However, because the formula is a bit more complicated, it may be more useful to use it only implicitly, and think about why your answer is right.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.33</term>. Suppose a quantity <m>Q= f(t)</m> grows exponentially as a function of <m>t</m>, where <m>Q = 3</m> when <m>t=2</m>, and <m>Q</m> increases by <m>25\%</m> every time <m>t</m> increases by <m>20</m>. Find a formula for <m>Q</m> in terms of <m>t</m>.
				</p>

				<p>
					 Since <m>Q</m> grows by <m>25\%</m> each time <m>t</m> increases by <m>20</m>, each time <m>t</m> increases by <m>20</m>, the initial quantity will be multiplied by <m>1.25</m>. This means the exponent of <m>1.25</m> should be divided by <m>20</m>. Since the output is <m>3</m> when <m>t=2</m>, we can put <m>t-2</m> as the numerator in the exponent. Thus we have <me>Q = f(t) = 3(1.25)^{\frac{t-2}{20}}.</me> Now we may ask ourselves whether this behaves in the specified way:
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					Is <m>f(2) = 3</m>? Yes, <m>f(2) = 3(1.25)^{\frac{2-2}{20}} = 3</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					Is <m>Q</m> multiplied by an additional factor of <m>1.25</m> each time <m>t</m> increases by <m>20</m>. Yes, observe <me>\begin{aligned}
f(2) &amp; = &amp; 3\\
f(22) &amp; = &amp; 3(1.25)^{\frac{20}{20}} = 3(1.25)\\
f(42) &amp; = &amp; 3(1.25)^{\frac{40}{20}} = 3(1.25)^2\\
\ &amp; \vdots &amp; \\\end{aligned}</me>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					Thus we can see that this function behaves in the specified way. 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

				<p>
					Another form of an exponential function is indicated by the preceding example. Often, in real world applications, exponential functions are described by a constant percent growth rate.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>Percent Growth Rate Form of an Exponential Function</term><!-- linebreak -->Every exponential function <m>f(x) = ab^{x}</m> may be written in the form <me>f(x) = a(1+r)^{x}.</me> In this form <m>r = b-1</m> is the percent growth (when multiplied by <m>100\%</m>) for each unit increase in <m>x</m>. Note:
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					If <m>b&gt;1</m>, then <m>r&gt;0</m>. In this case <m>r</m> is just called the growth rate.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					If <m>0&lt;b&lt;1</m>, then <m>r&lt;0</m>. In this case <m>|r|</m> is the decay rate.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.34</term>. <em>In the function <m>Q=f(t) = 3(1.25)^{\frac{t-2}{20}}</m>, by what percent does <m>Q</m> grow per unit increase in <m>t</m>?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="applications-of-exponential-functions">
				<title>Applications of Exponential Functions</title>

				<p>
					Standard applications of exponential functions are those related to growth and decay. We will introduce these applications now, but investigate them further when we are equipped with logarithms. Logarithms will allow us to solve equations involving exponential functions.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.35</term>. Suppose a population of bacteria, <m>P</m>, in millions starts at <m>P = 4</m> and triples every six hours. Find a formula for <m>P</m> as a function of time <m>t</m>, in hours. By what percent does <m>P</m> change each hour?<!-- linebreak --> Using the point-factor-time interval idea, we find <me>P = 4(3)^{\frac{t}{6}}.</me> In order to find the growth rate, we must first find the growth factor <m>b</m>. This is done by applying exponent rules: <me>P = 4(\sqrt[6]{3})^{t}.</me> Hence the growth factor is <m>b = \sqrt[6]{3}\approx 1.201</m>. Hence the percent growth rate is about <m>20.1\%</m> per hour.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.36</term>. <em>Cesium-137 is a radioactive isotope formed in nuclear fission. Given that it decays at a rate of <m>2.27\%</m> per year, what equation would you need to solve in order to find its half-life (the time it takes for half of an initial quantity to remain)?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>
		</subsection>

		<subsection xml:id="power-functions">
			<title>Power Functions</title>

			<p>
				The last basic family of functions we study will also be a two-parameter family. This is the family of <em>power functions. These are functions of the form <me>f(x) = kx^{p}.</me> We call <m>k</m> the </em>coefficient of the power function and <m>p</m> the <em>exponent. There are no restrictions placed on <m>k</m> and <m>p</m>; they can be any constant.</em>**
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 5.37</term>. <em>What conditions on <m>k</m> and <m>p</m> would place a power function into one of the other families of functions we have studied (list all possibilities)? Explain.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 5.38</term>. <em>Are there any values of <m>k</m> and <m>p</m> such that a power function could be called an exponential function? Explain.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			<p>
				While the class of power functions still only has two parameters, we will see they are somewhat more complicated than the families of linear and exponential functions. Power functions can have a much wider array of graphs and may exhibit more complicated domains and ranges than linear or exponential functions. However, much of the complication can be worked out by remembering our rules of arithmetic.
			</p>


			<subsubsection xml:id="intro-to-power-functions">
				<title>Intro to Power Functions</title>

				<p>
					Consider the following three power functions:
				</p>

				<p>
					<me>f(x) = x^{4},\ \ g(x) = \frac{1}{x^4},\ \ \mbox{and}\ \ h(x) = x^{\frac{1}{4}}.</me> Their coefficients are all equal to one. Their exponents are <m>4</m>, <m>-4</m>, and <m>\frac{1}{4}</m>, respectively. The simplest of these to graph is <m>f</m>:
				</p>

				<p>
					We see from the graph that <m>f(x) = x^4</m> is similar in shape to <m>y = x^2</m>. The outputs are never negative because the exponent is even, and the minimum output is zero. We see that the outputs grow more rapidly than those of <m>y = x^2</m> when <m>|x|&gt;1</m> and decay to zero more rapidly when <m>|x|&lt;1</m>. This is simply a result of repeating the multiplication of <m>x</m> by itself four times instead of two. As the exponent grows, this effect is exaggerated.
				</p>

				<p>
					A slightly more complicated graph is that of <m>g(x)</m>:
				</p>

				<p>
					In this graph, we never see negative outputs because the exponent is even. However, we also never see zero as an output because a fraction is only zero when its numerator is zero at the same time its denominator is not zero. The most conspicuous behavior of this function is that as <m>|x|</m> gets large, <m>g(x)\to 0</m> and as <m>|x|</m> gets close to zero, <m>g(x)\to \infty</m>. This is a simple consequence of arithmetic; if you divide by a large number, the result is small and if you divide by a positive number very close to zero, the result is very large.
				</p>

				<p>
					Finally, we can graph <m>h(x) = x^{\frac{1}{4}}</m>:
				</p>

				<p>
					In this graph we notice that the domain is only non-negative <m>x</m>-values. This is because even roots of negative numbers are not defined. Also, even roots of numbers are defined to be positive, so the range is all <m>y \geq 0</m>. The shape of the graph can be seen by noting that if <m>y=x^{\frac{1}{4}}</m>, then <m>x=y^4</m>. This means that the graph of <m>y=x^{\frac{1}{4}}</m> is that of the positive half of <m>y=x^{4}</m>, but reflected across the line <m>y=x</m>.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.39</term>. <em>Sketch graphs of <m>f(x) = x^{3}</m>, <m>g(x) = x^{-3}</m>, and <m>h(x) = x^{\frac{1}{3}}</m>. What is the main difference between these graphs and the graphs given above, and how can you explain the difference in terms of basic arithmetic?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.40</term>. <em>For each of the following conditions on <m>k</m> and <m>p</m>, sketch a rough graph of <m>f(x) = kx^{p}</m>. Explain why your graph looks the way it does with one or two sentences, and also give the domain and range of the function.</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>k&gt;0</m>, <m>p</m> is a positive odd integer.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>k&lt;0</m>, <m>p</m> is a negative odd integer.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>k&gt;0</m>, <m>p</m> is <m>\frac{1}{n}</m> for an odd integer <m>n</m>.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em><m>k&lt;0</m>, <m>p</m> is a negative even integer.</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>
		</subsection>

		<subsection xml:id="logarithms">
			<title>Logarithms</title>

			<p>
				When working with any family of functions, two common tasks are finding a formula for a member of some specified family satisfying some conditions (often points on the graph), and solving equations involving members of that family. A little reflection on the last two families we studied (exponential and power functions) reveals that we did not solve equations involving exponential functions or find formulas for power functions. This is because we need a way of solving for a variable in an exponent, which is exactly what <em>logarithms are for.</em>
			</p>

			<p>
				Before giving the definition of a logarithm, it may be helpful to think about the difference between a power function and an exponential function one more time. (<term>This is important, don’t skip reading it!</term>) A power function is one of the form <me>f(x) = kx^p.</me> Thinking about such a function as a process applied to the input, <m>x</m>, we would say <m>f</m>
			</p>

			<p><ul>
				<li>
							<p>
				raises <m>x</m> to the <m>p</m>-th power, then
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				multiplies the result by <m>k</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ul></p>

			<p>
				In order to describe what an exponential function, <me>g(x) = ab^x,</me> does to <m>x</m>, we need the following math verb: <em>to exponentiate (with a given base). The we can describe what <m>g</m> does as</em>
			</p>

			<p><ul>
				<li>
							<p>
				exponentiates <m>x</m> given a base of <m>b</m>, then
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				multiplies the result by <m>a</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ul></p>

			<p>
				This distinction of what is done to <m>x</m> by these families is deeper than just where <m>x</m> is as a symbol; it tells us which operation must be applied to undo each process. In the both cases, undoing the function first involves division (by <m>k</m> or <m>a</m>). Then, in the case of a power function, you undo raising <m>x</m> to the <m>p</m>-th power by taking the <m>p</m>-th root (equivalently, raising to the <m>\frac{1}{p}</m>-th power). In the case of the exponential function, we must undo exponentiation with a logarithm.
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
			<p>
				<term>Definition of <m>\log_{b}(y)</m></term><!-- linebreak -->The <em>logarithm, base <m>b</m>, of <m>y</m> is defined as follows:</em>
			</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
			<p>
				<m>x = \log_b(y)</m> is the inverse function of <m>y = b^{x}</m>.
			</p><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

			<p>
				Other ways of conceptualizing <m>\log_{b}(y)</m> are as follows:
			</p>

			<p><ul>
				<li>
							<p>
				<m>\log_{b}(b^x)=x</m> and <m>b^{\log_{b}(y)} = y</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				The base <m>b</m> logarithm undoes exponentiation with base <m>b</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				The equation <m>\log_b(y) = x</m> is equivalent to <m>b^{x} = y</m>.
			</p>
				</li>

			</ul></p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 5.41</term>. <em>Find the following logarithms:</em>
			</p>

			<p><ol>
				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\log_{2}(32)</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\log_{3}\left(\frac{1}{9}\right)</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\log_{100}(10)</m></em>
			</p>
				</li>

				<li>
							<p>
				<em><m>\log_{b}(1)</m> (no matter what <m>b</m> is)</em>
			</p>
				</li>

			</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 5.42</term>. <em>Suppose that <m>b&gt;1</m>. Explain why <m>\log_{b}(y)</m> is positive when <m>y&gt;1</m> and <m>\log_{b}(y)</m> is negative when <m>y&lt;1</m>.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
			<p>
				<term>Question 5.43</term>. <em>Explain why <m>\log_b(0)</m> is undefined.</em>
			</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			<p>
				One of the major difficulties of logarithms is that they cannot easily be computed by hand unless the input is an obvious power of the base; a calculator is usually required. However, there are only two logarithms programmed into most calculators, the <em>common logarithm and the </em>natural logarithm. The common logarithm has a base of ten and the natural logarithm has a base of <m>e \approx 2.718</m>. We will focus our use on the common logarithm. We will see in the next section that you really only need one logarithm.**
			</p>


			<subsubsection xml:id="logarithm-properties-and-solving-equations">
				<title>Logarithm Properties and Solving Equations</title>

				<p>
					From now on we will only use one logarithm, <m>\log(y) = \log_{10}(y)</m>.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="tcolorbox"-->
				<p>
					<term>Properties of <m>\log</m></term><!-- linebreak -->The following properties of the common logarithm follow from familiar exponent rules:
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<m>\log(AB) = \log(A) + \log(B)</m> (from <m>a^{m}a^{n} = a^{m+n}</m>)
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>\log\left(\frac{A}{B}\right) = \log(A) - \log(B)</m> (from <m>\frac{a^{m}}{a^{n}} = a^{m-n}</m>)
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<m>\log(A^p) = p\log(A)</m> (from <m>(a^{n})^m = (a^{m})^n = a^{mn}</m>)
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="tcolorbox">-->

				<p>
					<term>Justification:</term> We will justify the first property and leave the other two as an exercise. To justify the first property, observe that <m>\log(AB)</m> is the exponent of <m>10</m> that yields <m>AB</m>, i.e. <me>10^{\log(AB)} = AB.</me> If we can show that <m>\log(A)+\log(B)</m> has the same property, then property one will be proven. If we exponentiate <m>\log(A) + \log(B)</m>, then we have <me>10^{(\log(A)+\log(B))} = 10^{\log(A)}10^{\log(B)} = AB.</me> Since both <m>\log(AB)</m> and <m>\log(A)+\log(B)</m> yield <m>AB</m> when we exponentiate them with a base of <m>10</m>, we have <m>\log(A)+\log(B) = \log(AB)</m>. 
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.45</term>. <em>Justify properties two and three in the same manner as property one was justified.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.46</term>. <em>Use the second logarithm property and the result of question 5.30, part (d), to show that <me>\log\left(\frac{1}{A}\right) = -\log(A).</me></em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.47</term>. In this example we see why the common logarithm is the only one we really need (although the natural logarithm is the most commonly used), as well as how we can use a logarithm to solve a simple equation. Suppose we wish to know the solution to <me>3^{x}  = 7.</me> The simple answer is <m>x = \log_{3}(7)</m>. However, we cannot get a decimal approximation of this from our calculator. We can take the common logarithm of both sides of the equation <me>\log(3^{x}) = \log(7).</me> Then by property three given above (you will use this property most often), we have <me>x\log(3) = \log(7).</me> Hence <m>x = \dfrac{\log(7)}{\log(3)}\approx 1.77</m>. In general, <me>\log_{b}(y) = \frac{\log(y)}{\log(b)}.</me>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

				<p>
					Now that we are equipped with logarithms, we can solve equations involving exponential expressions.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.48</term>. Suppose we wish to solve the equation <me>3\cdot 4^{x} = 5^{3x}.</me> A good first step in the process is to simplify this into an equivalent equation of the form <me>b^{x} = \mbox{a number}.</me> Then we can use our new tool to undo the exponentiation. Simplifying we have <me>\begin{aligned}
3\cdot 4^{x} &amp; = &amp; 5^{3x}\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \mbox{divide by}\ 3\  \mbox{and}\  5^{3x}= 125^x\\
\left(\frac{4}{125}\right)^{x} &amp; =&amp; \frac{1}{3}.\end{aligned}</me> Now we take the common logarithm of both sides of the equation and use the third logarithm property to get <me>x\log\left(\frac{4}{125}\right) = \log\left(\frac{1}{3}\right).</me> Then we simply divide to solve for <m>x</m>: <me>x = \frac{\log\left(\frac{1}{3}\right)}{\log\left(\frac{4}{125}\right)}.</me> This expression for <m>x</m> simplifies to <me>x = -\frac{\log{3}}{\log{4}-\log{125}}\approx .319.</me>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.49</term>. <em>Say exactly which logarithm properties are used in simplifying <m>\frac{\log\left(\frac{1}{3}\right)}{\log\left(\frac{4}{125}\right)}</m> to <m>-\frac{\log{3}}{\log{4}-\log{125}}</m>.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="applications-to-exponential-and-power-functions">
				<title>Applications to Exponential and Power Functions</title>

				<p>
					Now we are equipped to handle some problems involving exponential and power functions.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.50</term>. Suppose the balance in a bank account begins at <m>\$13,000</m> and earns <m>2.2\%</m> interest per year. When will there be <m>\$20,000</m> in the account?
				</p>

				<p>
					First, we need to find a formula for the amount <m>A</m> in the account, in dollars, as a function of the time <m>t</m>, in years. We can quickly determine this to be <me>A = 13000(1.022)^{t}.</me> Now we are faced with solving the equation <me>13000(1.022)^t = 20000.</me> Quick simplification and application of the technique from the previous section gives us <me>\begin{aligned}
(1.022)^t &amp; =  &amp; \frac{20}{13}\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
\log((1.022)^t)) &amp; = &amp; \log\left(\frac{20}{13}\right)\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
t\log(1.022) &amp; = &amp;  \log\left(\frac{20}{13}\right)\\
 &amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
t &amp; = &amp; \frac{\log(20)-\log(13)}{\log(1.022)}\approx 19.8.\end{aligned}</me> Hence there will be <m>\$20,000</m> in the account in about 19.8 years.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.51</term>. <em>Consider a bank account that initially begins with <m>\$20,000</m> and only earns a <m>1.5\%</m> annual interest rate. After how many years will the account from the previous example be worth more than this account? Give your answer in exact form (with logarithms) as well as a deimal approximation using a calculator.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.52</term>. Suppose a population of bacteria begins at 1,000 and grows at a rate of <m>6\%</m> per hour. What is the doubling-time of this population?<!-- linebreak --> First we find a formula for the population, <m>P</m>, as a function of time, <m>t</m>, in hours: <me>P  = 1000(1.06)^t.</me> The doubling-time will then be the time it takes for the population to be <m>2,000</m>, so we solve: <me>\begin{aligned}
1000(1.06)^t &amp; = &amp; 2000\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
(1.06)^t &amp; = &amp; 2\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
t\log(1.06) &amp; = &amp; \log(2)\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
t &amp; = &amp; \frac{\log(2)}{\log(1.06)}\approx 11.9.\end{aligned}</me> Thus the population will double in about 11.9 hours.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.53</term>. <em>Use some part of the solution in the previous example to explain why the doubling-time (or half-life) of an exponentially growing (or decaying) quantity is independent of its initial value.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.54</term>. Find a formula for a power function <m>f(x) = kx^{p}</m> such that <m>f(1) = 3</m> and <m>f(4) = 7</m>.<!-- linebreak --> First we note that <m>f(1) = k\cdot 1^{p} = k</m>. Thus, <m>k=3</m>. We can substitute the other point and use logarithms to solve for <m>p</m>: <me>\begin{aligned}
3\cdot 4^{p} &amp; = &amp; 7\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
4^{p} = \frac{7}{3}\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
p\log(4) &amp; = &amp; \log(7)-\log(3)\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
p &amp; = &amp; \frac{\log(7)-\log(3)}{\log(4)}\approx 0.611.\end{aligned}</me> Thus the function of interest is approximately (due to approximating the logarithms) <m>f(x) = 3x^{0.611}</m>. <term>Note:</term> You should leave logarithmic expressions in exact form when possible; if you substitute decimal approximations at various steps of the problem, the error can propagate very quickly.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.55</term>. <em>Answer the following questions about the last example:</em>
				</p>

				<p><ol>
					<li>
									<p>
					<em>What mistake in the last step of solving for <m>p</m> might lead you to conclude <m>p=1</m>?</em>
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					<em>Once you know <m>k=3</m>, how can you tell that <m>p</m> must be less than one without actually solving for it?</em>
				</p>
					</li>

				</ol></p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>
		</subsection>

		<subsection xml:id="graphical-transformations-and-function-families">
			<title>Graphical Transformations and Function Families</title>

			<p>
				In this section we discuss transformations of functions built out of the basic operations of arithmetic, applied to the inputs and/or outputs of the function. Such transformations are called graphical transformations because they can be visualized as moving the graph of a parent function. The idea of graphical transformations brings together the concept of functions, as sequential processes applied to the inputs to yield the output, together with the geometric understanding of arithmetic presented in Chapter 1.
			</p>


			<subsubsection xml:id="basic-graphical-transformations">
				<title>Basic Graphical Transformations</title>

				<p>
					Graphical transformations have two fundamental types: <em>inside transformations and </em>outside transformations. An inside transformation is some sequence of operations applied to the input before the function is evaluated, whereas an outside transformation is a sequence of operations applied after the function. For these transformations to have graphical meaning, we restrict ourselves to the following operations, applied to the input and/or output of a function <m>y=f(x)</m>:**
				</p>

				<p><ul>
					<li>
									<p>
					We may add or subtract a positive constant <m>a</m> to/from <m>x</m>, before <m>f</m> is applied. Then we have a new function <m>y = f(x+a)</m> or <m>y=f(x-a)</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					We may multiply <m>x</m> by a constant <m>k</m>, before <m>f</m> is applied. Then we have a new function <m>y = f(kx)</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					We may add or subtract a positive constant <m>a</m> to/from <m>f(x)</m>, after evaluation. Then we have a new function <m>y = f(x)+a</m> or <m>y=f(x)-a</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

					<li>
									<p>
					We may multiply <m>f(x)</m> by a constant <m>k</m>, after evaluation. Then we have a new function <m>y = kf(x)</m>.
				</p>
					</li>

				</ul></p>

				<p>
					In this list, the first two transformations are our basic inside transformations, the last two are our basic outside transformations.
				</p>

				<p>
					Because outside transformations are easier to explain, we will start with them. Consider a generic function <m>y = f(x)</m>, whose graph is shown below.
				</p>

				<p>
					If we build a new function <m>y = f(x) + a</m>, where <m>a</m> is a positive number, each output is increased by <m>a</m>. Hence, because of addition being represented as upward motion, the graph is shifted up by <m>a</m> units. Likewise, if the new function is <m>y = f(x)-a</m>, the graph is shifted down by <m>a</m> units (remember, we assumed <m>a</m> was positive). In the following figure, we have the graph of <m>f</m> along with its vertical shifts by <m>1</m> and <m>-1</m>.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.56</term>. <em>Let <m>f(x) = 3(0.5)^x</m>. What is the range of <m>f</m>? What is the range of <m>f(x) + a</m> when <m>a</m> is any number (not necessarily just positive)? Explain.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					Now we will move on to the effect of multiplication on the outside of a function. Suppose our parent function is <m>y=f(x)</m> and <m>k&gt;1</m>, then <m>y = kf(x)</m> has a graph that is that of <m>f</m>, except stretched away from the <m>x</m>-axis by a factor of <m>k</m>. this is due to the geometric representation of multiplication by numbers greater than one being represented as a stretch away from zero. Likewise, if <m>0&lt;k&lt;1</m>, then the graph is compressed vertically by a factor of <m>k</m>. If <m>k</m> is negative, then the graph is first reflected across the <m>x</m>-axis, then stretched or compressed by the magnitude of <m>k</m>. This is due to our representation of multiplication by negative numbers as reflection, followed by a stretch or compression.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.57</term>. <em>Suppose <m>f</m> has a horizontal intercept at <m>x=r</m>. Symbolically, this means <m>f(r) = 0</m>. What happens to the location of this intercept when the function is transformed into <m>kf(x)</m>? Explain both graphically and symbolically.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.58</term>. <em>Describe what happens to the <m>y</m>-intercept of a function under the action of each of the basic outside transformations.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					Now we will describe the effect of inside transformations. First, consider adding a positive number <m>a</m> to <m>x</m>, before <m>f</m> is applied. Because <m>a</m> is added to <m>x</m> before <m>f</m> is applied, the output of <m>f(x+a)</m>, for any given <m>x</m>, will be equal to the output of <m>f(x)</m> at a point <m>a</m> units to the right of <m>x</m>. Hence, we have the following:<!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
				<p>
					The graph of <m>f(x+a)</m> is the graph of <m>f(x)</m>, except shifted <m>a</m> units to the left.<!-- linebreak -->
				</p><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

				<p>
					Likewise, the graph of <m>f(x-a)</m> is that of <m>f(x)</m>, except shifted to the right by <m>a</m> units.
				</p>

				<p>
					This may seem counter intuitive at first, because adding should move things to the right. However, finding an <m>x</m>-value for a given <m>y</m>-value will involve solving for <m>x</m>, which means the last step we will do is subtract, i.e. move to the left. For instance, consider the following example:
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.59</term>. Let <m>f(x) = \sqrt{x-3} + 5</m>. One simple point on the graph of this function is <m>(4,6)</m>, because <m>f(4) = \sqrt{4-3} + 5 = 6</m>. Now let’s consider the new function <m>g(x) = f(x+2) = \sqrt{(x+2)-3} + 5</m>. To find the transformed version of <m>(4,6)</m> on the graph of <m>g</m>, we must solve: <me>\begin{aligned}
\sqrt{(x+2) - 3} + 5 &amp; = &amp; 6\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
(x+2) - 3 &amp; = &amp; 1\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
(x+2) &amp; = &amp; 4\\
&amp; \updownarrow &amp; \\
x = 2.\end{aligned}</me> Thus the transformed point is <m>(2,6)</m>, which is two units to the left of <m>(4,6)</m>.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.60</term>. <em>Let <m>f(x) = \frac{1}{(x+4)(x-5)}</m>. What is the domain of <m>f(x)</m>? What is the domain of <m>f(x-a)</m>, where <m>a</m> is a real number?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

				<p>
					Multiplication as an inside transformation is handled similarly to addition. Suppose <m>f</m> is a parent function, and we want to see the effect of multiplying <m>x</m> by some constant <m>k</m>, before <m>f</m> is applied. If <m>k&gt;1</m>, then for any given <m>x</m>, the output of <m>f(kx)</m> will be that of <m>f(x)</m> at a point that is a factor of <m>k</m> further away from the <m>y</m>-axis. Thus, when <m>k&gt;1</m>, we have<!-- linebreak -->
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="center"-->
				<p>
					The graph of <m>f(kx)</m> is the graph of <m>f(x)</m>, except compressed by a factor of <m>\frac{1}{k}</m> toward the <m>y</m>-axis.<!-- linebreak -->
				</p><!--</div attr= class="center">-->

				<p>
					Likewise, the graph of <m>f(kx)</m> is that of <m>f(x)</m>, except stretched away from the <m>y</m>-axis by a factor of <m>\frac{1}{k}</m> when <m>0&lt;k&lt;1</m> (so <m>\frac{1}{k} &gt; 1</m>). If <m>k</m> is negative, the graph of <m>f(kx)</m> is first reflected over the <m>y</m>-axis, then compressed or stretched according to the absolute value of <m>k</m>.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.61</term>. <em>Suppose <m>(2,3)</m> is on the graph of <m>y=f(x)</m>, that is <m>f(2) = 3</m>. What point is on the graph of <m>y = f(-2x) + 1</m>? Explain both graphically and symbolically.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

			</subsubsection>

			<subsubsection xml:id="function-families-and-graphical-transformations">
				<title>Function Families and Graphical Transformations</title>

				<p>
					Some of our important forms for certain function families may be thought of as graphical transformations of some building block members of the given family.
				</p>

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.62</term>. Consider the basic linear function with slope <m>m</m>, <m>y = f(x) = mx</m>. The <m>y</m>-intercept of this function is at <m>(0,0)</m>. In order to obtain a new linear function whose graph passes through the point <m>(x_0,y_0)</m>, we can perform a horizontal shift to the right by <m>x_0</m> units and a vertical shift up by <m>y_0</m> units to obtain <me>y = f(x-x_0) + y_0 = m(x-x_0) + y_0.</me> This is simply the point-slope form for a line with slope <m>m</m> passing through the point <m>(x_0,y_0)</m>.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="eg"-->
				<p>
					<term>Example 5.63</term>. Consider a basic quadratic function <m>f(x) = ax^2</m>, where <m>a</m> is some given number. The vertex of its graph is at <m>(0,0)</m>. In order to have the vertex occur at <m>(h,k)</m>, we simply shift it to get <me>y = f(x-h)+k = a(x-h)^2 + k.</me> This is the vertex form of a quadratic.
				</p><!--</div attr= class="eg">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.64</term>. <em>Use factored form to find the formula for a quadratic function <m>f(x)</m> whose <m>x</m>-intercepts are at <m>(1,0)</m> and <m>(4,0)</m>, and whose <m>y</m>-intercept is at <m>(0,7)</m>. What does the parameter <m>a</m> (which you must solve for) do graphically?</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->

<!-- div attr= class="question"-->
				<p>
					<term>Question 5.65</term>. <em>In building an exponential function, <m>Q = f(t)</m>, with an initial value of five that grows by <m>3\%</m> for each ten unit increase in <m>t</m>, we find <me>Q = f(t) = 5(1.03)^{t/10}.</me> Explain how this function can be built using two graphical transformations of <m>g(t) = (1.03)^t</m>.</em>
				</p><!--</div attr= class="question">-->
			</subsubsection>

		</subsection>

	</section>



</article>
</pretext>
